<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The mystery of atheism, or, The devices made use of to countenance and propagate it together with the evil and danger of them, set forth in several letters to a friend : wherein is made appear, that 'tis not want of evidence, but sincerity that makes men atheists / by the author of the Mystery of phanaticism.</title>
            <author>A. B.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 162 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 69 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51679</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M3183</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32115</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18185784</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18185784</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106946</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51679)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106946)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1128:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The mystery of atheism, or, The devices made use of to countenance and propagate it together with the evil and danger of them, set forth in several letters to a friend : wherein is made appear, that 'tis not want of evidence, but sincerity that makes men atheists / by the author of the Mystery of phanaticism.</title>
                  <author>A. B.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 128 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for A. and J. Churchil ... and sold by Rich. Gravell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>All letters signed: A.B.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Doctrines.</term>
               <term>Atheism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106946:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106946:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Myſtery <hi>of</hi> Atheiſm; OR THE DEVICES Made uſe of To Countenance and Propagate it: Together with the EVIL and DANGER of them. Set forth in ſeveral Letters to a Friend. Wherein is made appear, that 'tis not want of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, but Sincerity that makes Men Atheiſts. <hi>By the Author of the Myſtery of Phanaticiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſal. 14. 1.</bibl> 
               <hi>The Fool hath ſaid in his heart, there is no God.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>A.</hi> and <hi>J. Churchil,</hi> at the Black Swan in <hi>Pater-Noſter-Row.</hi> And ſold by <hi>Rich. Gravell,</hi> in <hi>Briſtal.</hi> 1699.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:106946:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106946:2"/>
            <head>The PREFACE.</head>
            <p>IF any be deſirous to know the occaſion of theſe Letters, he need only look abroad, and may ſoon ſee that there is but too much occaſion for them: For Atheiſm is ſo ſtrangely encreas'd among us of late Years, and grown to that heighth, that like a torrent it overflows the Banks and Boundaries of Laws, and hath almoſt carried away all Religion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it: So that 'tis high time to uſe our beſt Endeavours to ſtem this Tide, and if poſſible to put a ſtop to this overflowing of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>It hath been a matter hotly diſputed in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times, whether there ever was, or could be ſuch an Anomalous Creature as an Atheiſt; or if any Age had here and there afforded one, he was reputed a Monſter or Prodigy, and gaz'd upon as a Wonderful Rarity: But our Age hath put this matter out of Queſtion, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps afforded more than any that hath gone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it; this Monſter is now grown familiar, and may every day and almoſt every where be ſeen. Atheiſm in old times was ſo modeſt, as not to venture abroad without a Mask or Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe; but 'tis now become bare-fac'd, and hath
<pb facs="tcp:106946:3"/> caſt off all bluſhing and ſhame; and where as the fool in <hi>David's</hi> days only <hi>ſaid in his heart,</hi> in ours he ſpeaks out, and ſays with his Tongue, there is no God.</p>
            <p>'Twill be needleſs to recount here the extream Folly and Danger of Atheiſm, which the Reader will find in ſome meaſure done in the following Letters: If there be a God that made and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns the World, (as there is all the Reaſon in the World from the Make and Management of it to believe there is) what a vile affront muſt it be to Queſtion his Being, and to go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to argue him out of the World, that made and plac'd us in it? This muſt tear up all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion by the Root, ſubvert the Foundation of human Society, and deſtroy all that Truſt and Confidence we ought to have in him and one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother: Yea, the Atheiſt is the moſt groſs and ſilly of all Impoſtors, for he puts a cheat upon himſelf, and not only excludes him from all the Comfort and Happineſs he might hope from ſo lovely a Being, but expoſes himſelf to all that Miſery and Puniſhment, that may be fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from an incenſed Deity.</p>
            <p>And yet as ſilly as this is, he is not only willing to be thus groſsly deceiv'd himſelf, but is very buſie to draw in and deceive others, and to make Proſelytes to ſuch a ſenſeleſs and fatal impoſture; by which means the infection of this Evil ſpreads dayly, and the diſtemper is well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigh become Epidemical.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:106946:3"/>
            <p>Now this Myſtery of Iniquity working ſo ſtrongly in our days, and this <hi>Spiritual wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs being again ſeated in high places,</hi> 'twill be requiſite (if it may be) both to detect and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throne it. 'Tis indeed a matter Worthy the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry of the beſt and wiſeſt Men, to ſearch into the bottom of this Evil, that by knowing the Cauſe, they may the better apply timely Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies for the Cure of it, before the diſtemper grow inveterate and incurable; for tho' all ſin in general, yet an Atheiſtical Contempt of God, and boldneſs in ſinning, do more particularly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermine the Peace and Proſperity of a Nation, and more than ordinarily haſten and ripen it for deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Now tho' there may be ſome latent Cauſes of Atheiſm, that lye more hidden and out of ſight, yet there are others that are more viſible, and apparently lead to this great Evil: The looſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Principles of Religion and Government hath certainly a great hand in it; the diſſolv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Tyes of Juſtice and Honeſty does not a little contribute towards it, and the breaking the Bonds of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity and Peace have an eaſie and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural tendency to it: how much the immodeſty and immorality of the Stage hath tended this way, hath been lately ſhew'd by an excellent Pen; what miſchief hath proceeded from that other Stage, I mean the Conventicle, ſad experience may inform us; and how much Religion hath ſuffered by a new Set of Reformers, who are for
<pb facs="tcp:106946:4"/> Reforming all faults but their own, may be dayly ſeen; and this, as all other Myſteries, hath ſome depths and intrigues, which muſt be ſearcht into and laid open, before the evil can be prevented.</p>
            <p>'Twas foretold that in the latter days, ſome ſhould put on a <hi>Form of Godlineſs, without the Power of it;</hi> and likewiſe that <hi>there ſhould ariſe Scoffers, walking after their own Luſts:</hi> Both theſe Prophecies we may ſee accompliſh'd in our days, in which we find ſome acting very vile things under a Cloak of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and others throwing off all pretenſions to it, breaking thir jeſts upon God and Religion, and making the moſt Sacred and Serious things the Object of their Contempt and Raillery: And both theſe, tho' ſteering different courſes, fall at laſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Gulph of Atheiſm, in which many are ſwallowed up, and from whence few return.</p>
            <p>In a Word, Atheiſm is the Completion of Vice and Wickedneſs; in which they all center and terminate; ſo that this ſin when it is finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed bringeth forth death, and ſinks Men into e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting perdition. This then being an Evil ſo pernicious to the welfare of Mankind, as well as to the Honour of our Maker, 'twill be neceſſary to ſet forth the Arts by which it is diſguiſed and propagated, that we may behold this Monſter in its own ſhape, and be thereby in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to ſhun and deteſt it.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewel.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:106946:4"/>
            <head>The CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Letter 1.</hi> OF the Atheiſts caſting off the awe and ſenſe of a Deity, the better to enjoy and indulge his Luſts. <hi>page 1</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Letter 2.</hi> Of his ſolving the <hi>Phaenomena</hi> of the World without a Deity. <hi>p. 11</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Letter 3.</hi> Of his endeavouring to ſtifle the Convictions and Notices that Conſcience gives of a Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. <hi>p. 24</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Letter 4.</hi> Of his aſcribing the Notion of a God to eaſineſs of Belief and fond Credulity. <hi>p. 34</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Letter 5.</hi> Of his reſolving it into the Principles and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judices of Education. <hi>p. 43</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Letter 6.</hi> Of his attributing to Fear or a Superſtitious Dread of ſome inviſible Powers. <hi>p. 50</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Letter 7.</hi> His aſcribing it to State-Policy. <hi>p. 58</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Letter 8.</hi> Aſcribing it to Common Compact. <hi>p. 64</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Letter 9.</hi> His denial of the Notion and Being of a Spirit. <hi>p. 70</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:106946:5"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Letter 10.</hi> Of the unequal Diſtribution of Earthly things. <hi>p. 78</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Letter 11.</hi> Of his taking advantage from the Diſputes and Differences in Religion. <hi>p. 86</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Letter 12.</hi> His making uſe of the Hypocriſie of Pretenders to caſt off all Religion. <hi>p. 93</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Letter 13.</hi> Of Scoffing at Religion. <hi>p. 99</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Letter 14.</hi> His charging Religion with a Fooliſh Bargain. <hi>p. 106</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Letter 15.</hi> The Cloſe, containing ſome Directions for the Cure of Atheiſm. <hi>p. 113</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106946:5"/>
            <head>LETTER I.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Received yours, wherein I find you paſſionately bewailing the growth of Atheiſm; and very deſirous to know ſomething of the Cauſes and Cure of it.</p>
            <p>I am ſufficiently ſenſible of the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of the Complaint, and becauſe this Evil hath ſo malign an influence, not only on the private but publick Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, cannot but commend the Charity of your Requeſt, and therefore ſhall endeavour ſomething towards your Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>1ſt.</hi> And here the Firſt and Grand Device of the Atheiſt, that occurs to our view, is, The caſting off the awe and dread of a Deity, the more ſecure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to enjoy and indulge his Luſts: This is indeed the great depth of this My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of Iniquity, which muſt therefore be a little ſearcht into and unravell'd,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:106946:6"/> that we may the better ſee the malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of it.</p>
            <p>'Tis moſt certain, that the Looſneſs and Debauchery of mens lives is the prime fundamental Cauſe of all Atheiſm; for Sin and Wickedneſs make a Party againſt Religion, whoſe Chief deſign it is to check and controul them; and where Religion is not ſtrong enough to ſubdue mens Luſts, there mens Luſts will be ſtrong enough to ſubdue their Religion; theſe are contrary one to the other, and as the one gets ground, the other loſes it: When Vice and Wickedneſs have taken poſſeſſion of the heart, and prevail'd over the Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, they ſoon draw the Mind over to their Party, and engage it againſt all Religion. Corrupt Practices, naturally lead to Corrupt Principles; and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauchery of Manners, of courſe, brings on the debauchery of the Mind. That there are ſtrong Propenſities and Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in mens Natures, to wickedneſs and vice, is a thing too ſenſibly felt to need any proof; and that theſe may, and frequently do, wear off and obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate the Natural Impreſſions of Good and Evil, the Courſe of mens lives too ſadly verifies; and, what a natural ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:106946:6"/> this hath to Atheiſm, half an eye may diſcover. For, whilſt men retain any love to Virtue, and keep the maſtery over their Luſts and vile Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſo long they retain their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and keep up a due ſenſe and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of the Divine Majeſty! but when they ſtrike off from the love and practice of Virtue, and let looſe the reins to their vitious Inclinations, they naturally run into Irreligion and Atheiſm; for Virtue and Goodneſs being the only Curb to reſtrain this Extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance, when that is gone, they have nothing left to ſtop them in the Career, and ſo are hurried on headlong into the gulph of Atheiſm. If you obſerve it, Good men are never diſpos'd to Atheiſm; 'tis the grief and abhorrence, but never the Choice of ſuch Perſons: 'Tis only the profligate and prophane, who have ſinn'd away the ſenſe of a Deity, that fly to it for ſhelter: and to give their luſts the freer ſcope, make their laſt reſort to it. Yea, theſe too muſt in a great meaſure un-man themſelves, before they can ſo far degenerate; and in a manner turn Beaſts, before they can turn Atheiſts.</p>
            <p>But what influence hath the looſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:106946:7"/> and debauchery of mens lives up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the producing of Atheiſm? Why, Great every way. As,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Mens wicked lives make it their Intereſt that there ſhould be no God, and this gives a Biaſs to the mind that ſtrongly draws it into Atheiſm. All ſiin and wickedneſs being repugnant to the Purity and Perfection of a Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Being, and contrary to the expreſs Declarations of his Will, muſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily incur his diſpleaſure: And tho' In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Goodneſs may warn Sinners of the danger, yet Infinite Juſtice cannot ſuffer the wilful Violations of his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and Laws to go unpuniſh'd Now, reſolute and obſtinate Sinners being conſcious how they have affront<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſuch a Being, and thereby rendred themſelves obnoxious to his juſt Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and Vengeance, have all the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the world to dread him; and, if they can, to fly from him; from whom they can have no other than fearful Expectations of Wrath, and the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of Righteous Judgment: And having thus made him their Enemy 'tis plainly become their Intereſt that there ſhould be no ſuch Being. Now Intereſt (you know) hath a mighty In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:106946:7"/> on mens Inclinations; and as they eaſily believe what makes for them, ſo they are hardly perſwaded to that which makes againſt them: Hence we ſee, that Good men eaſily believe a God, from whom they have well-grounded hopes of Happineſs and a future Reward: whereas wicked men are very hardly brought to it, becauſe they have reaſon only to fear him, and can look for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but eternal miſery and deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from him: And if at any time they have any Faith in him, 'tis but like that of the Devils, to believe and tremble. Again,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly,</hi> Mens wicked lives having made it their Intereſt that there ſhould be no God, their next ſtep is to make it their wiſh that there were none. This is another piece of this Myſtery of Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and a farther advance to Atheiſm: For, the belief of an Incens'd Deity, muſt needs ſit very uneaſie upon the mind; it cannot but fret and gall, and fill it with continual horrour and perplexity: The Senſe of this ſerves to imbitter the Pleaſures of Sin, to put a check up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on mens Vices, and will not ſuffer them to enjoy their Luſts in quiet; which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reſolv'd to do, they grow impatient
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106946:8"/> under this Check: And this makes them deſirous to rid themſelves of the awe and ſenſe of ſuch an uneaſie Being. The good man finds that eaſe and ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction in the ſenſe of a Deity, that he wou'd not for any thing be without it, for it fills him with joy and content now, and gives him Peace and Happineſs at the laſt: Inſomuch, that were he to wiſn himſelf the Chiefeſt Good, it would be in the comfort and compla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence he feels in the belief of a Deity. Whereas the looſe and wicked perſon, is haunted with perpetual Fears and Terrors; and the diſquietude he feels, from the apprehenſions of a God, drives him to wiſh there were no ſuch Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to obſerve and puniſh him; and then a ſmall matter will perſwade him to it; for, <hi>Facilè credimus, quod volumus,</hi> we eaſily believe what we long and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire ſhould be true.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>3dly,</hi> And this leads to the third and laſt ſtep to Atheiſm, which is, from wiſhing there were no God, to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to perſwade themſelves that there is none; there being an eaſie and natural tranſition, from the one to the other: for the Will and Affections have a great ſway on the Underſtanding; and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:106946:8"/> when Intereſt hath engag'd the former, they ſoon draw the latter to their ſide; ſo that what men make their Wiſh, quickly becomes their Choice; and from a deſire to diſcard the Deity, eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly come to deny and disbelieve him.</p>
            <p>But by what Means do they endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and effect this? Why,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, They muſter up all their Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Wit to argue againſt the Being of a God, and ſeek to diſpute him out of the world. To this end, they labour, as well as they can, to weaken the force of all thoſe Arguments that are brought for the proof of a Deity, and make the beſt ſhift they can, either to anſwer or evade them. Again, they magnifie the ſtrength of thoſe Arguments that are brought againſt ſuch a Being: And, (tho' to prove a Negative, in this as in many other caſes, be both irrational and impoſſible, yet) to ſhew their good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will to their Maker, the ſlend'reſt Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils or Probabilities of this nature ſhall have a mighty force with them; and the ſlighteſt Sophiſtry be advanc'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Demonſtration. But if this will not do, they endeavour,</p>
            <p n="2">2. To baniſh all thoughts of God out of their mind, and to caſt off the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:106946:9"/> of him: Becauſe they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſin quietly for him, they reſolve not to think of him, and therefore put thoſe thoughts far from them that give them this diſturbance. This was the Atheiſts courſe in <hi>David</hi>'s time, who tells us, [<hi>That God was not in all their thoughts;</hi>] yea, that his thoughts were always grievous to them; and therefore they removed them far out of their ſight, that they might have no <hi>fear of him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their Eyes:</hi> And the thoughts of a God that obſerves and records our Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and will one day reckon for them, are ſtill irkſom and grievous to impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent ſinners, which makes them uſe their Art to get rid of them. Indeed, could they but reconcile the belief of a Deity, with the enjoyment of their luſts, the thoughts of him would be eaſie e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to them; and this temptation to Atheiſm in a great meaſure ceaſe. Could they ſerve the true God, as the Heathens did the falſe ones, with riot and uncleaneſs, none would be greater Votaries than they: But ſince the ſenſe of him ſtrikes ſuch a damp upon their Pleaſures, and puts ſuch a curb and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint upon their Vices, they cannot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with the thoughts of him, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:106946:9"/> therefore labour to rid their minds of the belief, that they may be rid of the fear of ſuch a Being. But, is this a wiſe or ſafe courſe? No, extremely fooliſh and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous: for, tho 'it be weakneſs to fear where no fear is, yet not to fear where there is a juſt cauſe and a proper Object for it, is the height of Folly: And, to ſhut our Eyes againſt a certain Danger, for fear of being frightned by it, is no better than madneſs. Indeed, could we put out the Sun by winking, or avoid the danger of Divine Vengeance, by ſhaking off the dread of it, there might be ſome ſhew of Reaſon for our Unbelief; but, ſince the truth of things depends not upon our belief or disbelief of them; and the very Notion of a Deity implies a neceſſity of Exiſtence, it muſt be mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrouſly ſenſeleſs and unreaſonable, to caſt off the awe and dread of him.</p>
            <p>Again, To regulate our Faith by inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and affection, is to walk by a falſe and crooked Rule: For, theſe being fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently corrupted, clap a wrong Biaſs upon the Mind, which too often turns it from the Truth, and turns it unto Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles: And conſequently, to ſteer our courſe by theſe meaſures, is to follow a
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:106946:10"/> falſe Guide, which muſt lead us out of our way. Indeed, would men rightly underſtand and follow their true Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, it would then lead them aright into the paths of Religion, there being no comfort or ſecurity at all to be had with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it: But, when they weakly miſtake their Intereſt, and vainly wiſh there were no Superior Being to obſtruct it, they do but court miſery, and fondly chuſe their own deſtruction.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, the vaſt riſque that theſe men run, plainly ſhews it to be extreme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unſafe and dangerous: For, if the Atheiſt find at laſt that there is a God, whom he hath all his life-time deny'd and deſpis'd, what unſpeakable Horror muſt ſeize his guilty Soul, which muſt groan for ever under the wrath of ſuch an Almighty Being, and be eternally miſerable without eaſe or remedy? The Good-man runs no riſque at all, for the ſenſe of ſuch a Being hath made him more healthful and eaſie to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, more uſeful and ſerviceable to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and more honoured and reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of all men for both: And if there be no God at laſt, he can find no incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience in this belief; but if there be
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106946:10"/> one, he hath infinitely the better on't; being ſure to be Eternally Happy in his favour and preſence.</p>
            <p>So that if this were but a doubtful Caſe, common prudence teaches men to chuſe the ſafeſt ſide; to which therefore 'twill be our Wiſdom to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline. I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Your hearty Friend, A. B.</signed>
               <date>October 16. 1698.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="letter">
            <head>LETTER II.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Find you ſenſible, in your laſt, of the great evil and danger of that Artifice which hath drawn ſo many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Atheiſm, (<hi>viz.</hi>) The caſting off the awe and ſenſe of a Deity, that they may go on the more ſecurely in their Sins. I proceed in this to another De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice made uſe of to the ſame purpoſe,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:106946:11"/> (and that is) ſome Mens endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſolve the <hi>Phaenomena</hi> of the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſe, and to give an account of the Exiſtence of the World without a Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Being.</p>
            <p>'Tis well known, that one of the Principal Arguments and Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of a Deity, is taken from the Works both of Creation and Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; [<hi>The Inviſible things of God from the Creation of the World, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing clearly ſeen, even his Eternal Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Godhead.</hi>] And 'tis evident, (as the ſame Apoſtle told the Men of <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra) [That God hath not left himſelf with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out witneſs, in that he doth good, and giveth rain from Heaven, and fruitful ſeaſons, filling our hearts with food and gladneſs.</hi>] Indeed, the admirable frame and order of the World, together with the wonderful Proviſion made for all the Creatures in it, plainly beſpeak an Almighty Agent, to be both the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triver and Preſerver of it: Yea, there are thoſe viſible marks of an Infinite Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, Wiſdom and Goodneſs, ſtampt upon every Creature, that manifeſtly ſhew the Finger of a God; and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect our Minds to the Knowledge and Contemplation of him.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:106946:11"/>
            <p>Now to evade this clear and pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable Proof of his Being, the Atheiſt racks his Brain to find out a way of accounting for theſe things, without a firſt Cauſe or Orderer of them. And of theſe there are two ſorts, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt, Of thoſe that aſſert the Eternity of the World.</p>
            <p>The other, Of ſuch as make it the Product of Chance and Fortune. The Former, are the followers of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> and the Latter of <hi>Epicurus.</hi> Both which ſhew their great unwillingneſs to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve a Deity; and how deſirous they are <hi>to live without God in the World.</hi> But let us Examine the Account they give us of theſe Matters. To which end, let us begin with the firſt ſort.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>1ſt.</hi> Who, to ſet aſide a Firſt Cauſe, affirm the World to have had no beginning, but to have been from Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, as it now is; there having been an Eternal Succeſſion of Men and all other Creatures, as we now find it.</p>
            <p>Now, what proof is offer'd for this bold Affirmation? Why, none at all, 'tis a precarious Aſſertion, taken up from the ſingle Opinion of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any offer of Proof, or colour of Reaſon; and only ſhews that ſome
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:106946:12"/> Men have a mind to have it ſo; and would fain perſuade themſelves and others to it, if they can. And yet this Opinion, as deliver'd by <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> ſerves not the Atheiſt's turn neither: For, tho' he affirmed the World to have no Beginning, yet he ſaid not 'twas of its ſelf; but that it proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from God, by the way of a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural and neceſſary Effect, as light does from the Sun. Where there is a plain Confeſſion of a God, from whom the World and all things in it ſprang by a Natural and Eternal Emanation. So that he did not, with the Modern Atheiſts, ſet up the Notion of the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the World, to exclude a Firſt Cauſe, but thought it to be conſiſtent with it.</p>
            <p>But is there any Proof that the World had a Beginning, and that there is a Firſt Cauſe and Maker of it? Yes, as great as the Nature of the thing is capable of; which being a matter of Fact of an ancient Date, can only be prov'd by Teſtimony, and the fair appearances of Reaſon: And if both theſe concur in the matter before us, 'tis as much as the thing will bear;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:106946:12"/> and conſequently, as much as any wiſe man will require.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>1ſt.</hi> And Firſt, that the World was made and had a Beginning, we have the Teſtimony of all Mankind from the firſt making of it; there being an Univerſal Tradition hereof, deliver'd down thro' every Age ſince its Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning. The <hi>Egyptians,</hi> and <hi>Phoeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians</hi> of old; the <hi>Grecians, Aſſyrians, Perſians,</hi> and <hi>Romans,</hi> of latter Date, all had, and handed down this Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. Yea, the <hi>Indians</hi> and all other the moſt rude and barbarous Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that had little or no Commerce with other Nations, concurr'd in this Belief; all of them worſhiping a God, whom they own'd to be the Maker and Governour of the World. And tho' ſome difference hath been found about the Computation of Time, and the Age of the World, yet all agree in this, that it was made. Yea, we find <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> himſelf, who was the firſt Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerter of the Eternity of the World, (in his Book <hi>De Mundo,</hi> Chap. <hi>6th</hi>) freely confeſſing, that 'twas a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Tradition among all Men, that all things are of God, and were made by him.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:106946:13"/>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly.</hi> Again, <hi>Secondly,</hi> we find this Univerſal Tradition confirmed by the written Hiſtories of all Times and Places ever ſince. If we allow <hi>Moſes</hi> the Credit of the firſt and ancienteſt Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorian (which cannot be in Reaſon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied him) we have a full and conſiſtent Relation of the Beginning of the World and all things in it, which hath been receiv'd, and recorded from him in all ſucceeding Ages; and is moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable with the Account which all other Ancient Writers, whether Poets or Philoſophers, give of this matter, being in all probability derived from him: Inſomuch, that we find <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> himſelf (in his Book <hi>De Coelo, lib. 1. cap.</hi> 10) once more acknowledging, that all the Philoſophers that were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, did hold that the World was made.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>3dly.</hi> Moreover, <hi>Thirdly,</hi> we can trace up the Original of all Arts and Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, in the ſeveral Times and Places, when, and where they were firſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented: Which, if the World were E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal, would have been found out long before, and been known far be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all Memory: Unleſs we can ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that all Men in the Ages be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:106946:13"/> we have any Account, paſſed an Eternity in a deep Sleep; and were all ſo dull, as either to do nothing Memorable, or to be unable or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to Record it. And therefore <hi>Lucretius</hi> wiſely aske the Queſtion, If the World had no Beginning, how comes it to paſs, that the moſt Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Poets mention nothing higher than the <hi>Theban</hi> War, and the Deſtruction of <hi>Troy?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And indeed, if the World had no beginning, it is ſtrange that no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count ſhould be given of any thing in that Eternity of Duration, before the World is ſaid to begin: And that all things that are known, ſhould be found out and Recorded ſince that time.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Beſides <hi>Fourthly,</hi> We ſee the ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry parts of which the World conſiſts, to be ſubject to decay and Corruption; and had they been ſo from all Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, they muſt in all probability have utterly periſh'd and come to nothing long ſince. The Frame of the World, is compos'd of ſuch frail Corruptible Materials, that, in an infinite ſpace, would neceſſarily diſſolve, and fall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder, without a Superiour Power to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:106946:14"/> uphold and keep the parts together. This we may ſee excellently urg'd by <hi>Lucretius</hi> (Lib. 5.) where he tells us, <q rend="inline">That the World muſt neceſſarily be acknowledg'd to have had a begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, otherwiſe, thoſe things which are in their own Nature corruptible, could never, from all Eternity, have held out againſt all the forcible and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent Aſſaults and Accidents, which in an infinite duration muſt have happen'd to them.</q> And therefore wefind, that <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> having affirm'd the World to have had no beginning, was thereby driven in his own defence, to affirm, it can have no end; for what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever hath an end, muſt have a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning: And if the Frame of the World be Subject to Diſſolution, it could not poſſibly have been from E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity. In ſhort, we plainly ſee, that all things are ſome way or other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd; every man is of another; and every other thing hath ſome Cauſe of his Being, which muſt neceſſarily lead up to a firſt Cauſe, which is of its ſelf, and made and preſerves all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: And if the World had no begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, we may ſafely conclude, it muſt long ſince have had an end. So that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:106946:14"/> this Firſt <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> of the Eternity of the World, taken up without any proof, upon the ſingle Authority of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> againſt the Univerſal Belief and Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of Mankind, is, both unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and unaccountable.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let us proceed then, <hi>Secondly,</hi> to that of <hi>Epicurus,</hi> and ſee whether that be any better. And here, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude a Deity or firſt Cauſe, we find him affirming, that the World was made by Chance, and all things in it came together of themſelves, by ſome lucky Hits and Accidents: An account whereof is briefly this, (<hi>viz.</hi>) <q rend="inline">They tell us, that the Matter of which the World was fram'd, was from Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; and likewiſe, an Infinite emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſpace, for the innumerable ſmall Particles (call'd Atomes) to move and play in: And that theſe being in continual motion, did after infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Tryals and Rencounters, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the help or direction of a Supreme Being, by lucky Hits and Chances, ſettle at laſt in that goodly Frame and Order of things, which we now ſee, and find the World to be in.</q>
            </p>
            <p>A goodly account indeed! Which ſerves only to ſhew, that ſome men
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:106946:15"/> are willing to believe any thing ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than a God. For, who ever heard of a Houſe that was made without Hands? Or a Book compos'd by an accidental jumbling and meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together of Letters and Syllables of their own accord? And yet, This is far more eaſie to be imagin'd, than for ſo Stately and Beautiful a Structure as this of the World, to be rais'd without an Artificer: Or the great Volume of the Univerſe, to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pil'd without an Author. But, what Foundation hath this vain and incredible <hi>Hypotheſis?</hi> Why, none but the bold confidence of <hi>Epecurus</hi> and his Followers, grounded upon a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of letting looſe the Reins to his Appetite, and enjoying ſenſual Pleaſures without controul. Indeed, there can be no poſſible evidence of the World's being thus made by chance: For, theſe Atomes of which he ſpeaks are altogether inviſible; and, for ought we know, move on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the empty ſpace of an <hi>Fpicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rean</hi> Brain. Yea, there is all ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable Evidence to the contrary: For, there are thoſe apparent Marks of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:106946:15"/> Infinite Power and Wiſdom in the Frame of the World, that render it altogether impoſſible to be the effect of Chance: for, ſince none could ever ſpeak of a Structure, where all the parts of it came together of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and we never read of any thing Great and Noble, that was ever effected or came to paſs that way; how ſenſeleſs is it to conceive, that this glorious and regular Fabrick of the World, which affords as many Wonders as Parts, ſhould be the work of any other than a Divine Hand.</p>
            <p>So that the Folly of this Device, of giving an account of the Being and continuance of the World, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Deity, is very apparent; for it contradicts the Reaſon and Senſe of Mankind in all Ages; and oppoſes a Truth, that hath ſwim'd down the Current of time without inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption. Neither is the Evil and Danger leſs viſible, than the Folly of it: For, this is the higheſt Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front and Indignity that can be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd to our Maker, to rob him of the Honour of his Works, and to deny him the Glory that ſhould ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crue from them. There is certainly
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:106946:16"/> a Tribute of Honour and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment due to the Soveraign Lord and Maker of the Univerſe; which is to be paid by all his Creatures, but eſpecially by Man, who is made the viſible Lord and Vice-Roy of this lower World: Now, to call in queſtion his making or right of govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the World, is to deny him this Homage; and conſequently to prove Rebellious to our Supreme Lord and Maſter; which muſt needs be a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of extreme and inconceivable dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</p>
            <p>Again, <hi>2dly.</hi> 'Tis a high piece of Ingratitude to diſown our Maker and chiefeſt Benefactour, from whom we receive Life and Breath and all things; and to whom we owe therefore our loudeſt Praiſes and Thankſgivings: And when all other Creatures in, their way, ſhew forth the Glory of God, what Unworthineſs is it in Man, who was chiefly deſign'd for that end, to with-hold it from him: This is, not only negligently to obſerve the Works of the Lord, but utterly to diſclaim and forget the Operations of his Hand: Which muſt needs ſink him who was made ſomewhat high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:106946:16"/> than the Angels, into a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition lower and worſe than the Beaſt that periſheth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>3dly.</hi> Yea (<hi>Thirdly</hi>) This is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a high piece of injuſtice and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude to our Maker, but a great injury to Mankind; who are hereby depriv'd of that Aſſiſtance and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance, they might have in a Supreme Being; and conſequently of that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and benefit they might receive from him. We dayly ſee what impotent and feeble Creatures, even the beſt of Men are; liable to a thouſand miſeries and misfortunes, which they can neither prevent nor remove: Now the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly comfort or relief we can have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Theſe; is, in the Apprehenſions of a God, who is of infinite Power and Goodneſs; and conſequently, both able and willing to help us: There we may ſafely repoſe our Truſt and Confidence, with well-grounded hopes of a ſupply of all our wants, and a happy iſſue out of all our afflictions: Now, by calling in Queſtion the Truth of ſuch a Being, who is the Author and diſpoſer of ſuch Events, Men bereave themſelves of all theſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable expectations, and make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:106946:17"/> miſerable by their own Infidelity. So that this Device of the Atheiſt, is as imprudent as 'tis unreaſonable; for it deprives him of all that comfort, which he might have in this Life; and excludes him from all that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, to which he was deſign'd in the next.</p>
            <p>Theſe are obvious Truths, on which I ſhall not need to enlarge; and ſhall therefore leave them to your farther Meditation. I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>
                  <hi>SIR,</hi> 
               </salute>
               <signed>Your true Friend, A. B</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="letter">
            <head>LETTER III.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN your laſt I find you readily own the works of Creation and Providence to be palpable Demonſtrations of a Deity, and wonder at the Atheiſts blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:106946:17"/> or boldneſs in ſo eaſily overlook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or gainſaying them.</p>
            <p>I proceed in this to another Device to the ſame purpoſe, and that is the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencing the Voice of Conſcience, and ſtifling the frequent Notices and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larms it gives of a Supreme Being: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the other witneſſes that God hath left us of himſelf, that of Conſcience is none of the leaſt, which for the clear and uncontrolable Evidence of its Teſtimony, hath been reckon'd more than a thouſand witneſſes. That we might not be left without ſufficient Light in a matter of ſo great moment, God Almighty hath not only Engraven his own Image and Superſcription up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Works of his Hand, that by the frequent viewing thereof, we might be ſtill minded of him, but hath likewiſe ſet up a conſtant Monitor in every Man's Breaſt, that by hearkening to it we might never forget him: This is that which is ſtil'd the Light of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and by ſome the Light within them, which, if rightly underſtood, muſt be meant of this Directive Light of their own Mind or Conſcience: <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ſtiles <hi>it, the Candle of the Lord,</hi> to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:106946:18"/> light us in the way, that we ſhould go. The Prophet <hi>Iſaias</hi> calls it, <hi>a voice behind or within us, ſaying, this is the way walk in it, when we are turning either to the right hand or to the left.</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> told the Gentiles, that tho' they had no <hi>written Law, yet they were a Law to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, their Conſcience bearing witneſs, and their thoughts accuſing or excuſing one another,</hi> Rom. 2. And withal adds, that as God hath not <hi>left himſelf without witneſs,</hi> having given ſufficient notice of his Being; ſo he had left them, <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out excuſe,</hi> if they did not Worſhip and Glorifie him as they ought.</p>
            <p>But how does Conſcience give this notice and conviction of a Deity? Why, ſundry ways; as,</p>
            <p>Firſt, By its ſecret motions and ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions, which oft-times awakens our Mind, and powerfully ſtirs us up to our duty to him: If we obſerve it, we ſhall find and feel ſomething within us moving, and loudly calling upon us to that which is good; and ſecretly whiſpering and diſſuading us againſt that which is evil: Now theſe are the private Notices of Conſcience, which God hath ſet up as a Remembrancer
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:106946:18"/> and witneſs of him within our Breaſts. Again,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly.</hi> We feel an inward delight and complacence in well-doing, and are fill'd with joy and peace in believing: Now, whence ſhould this proceed, but from the ſecret notice of Conſcience, which minds us of a God, and that what we have done is acceptable and well-pleaſing to him? The good Man (ſaith <hi>Solomon) is ſatisfied from himſelf,</hi> that is from his own Conſcience, which he ſtiles a continual Feaſt, that enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains him with the ſweeteſt peace and tranquility of mind, and fills him with purer joys, than any earthly comforts can afford him, even with joy unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and full of Glory, ariſing from a Belief that God is, and that he is a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warder of all thoſe that diligently ſeek him. Moreover,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>3dly.</hi> The Sinner feels ſecret Stings and Laſhes within, when he hath done amiſs, and is inwardly troubled and perplex'd after the Commiſſion of any Enormity; his Debaucheries grate up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his mind, and follow him with fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent fears and terrors; there is no peace to the wicked; but they are like the troubled Sea that cannot reſt.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:106946:19"/> Now, this can proceed from nothing but the inward whiſpers and informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Conſcience, which frequently takes the Sinner aſide, and rates him ſoundly by himſelf, letting him know how he hath offended his Maker, and thereby juſtly incurr'd the diſmal effects of his diſpleaſure; hence the Sinner feels many ſharp girds and twitches within, even for Sins known to none but God and himſelf: Which know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge proceeds from this ſecret Moni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, who is both an Accuſer, Witneſs, and Judge, all which Offices it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly performs with great fidelity and diligence; inſomuch that if there be no God to be feared by us, we might envy the happineſs of brute Beaſts, who have none of theſe frights, nor are troubled with any of theſe ſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Reflections: Yea Mankind, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Deity, would be not only the moſt miſerable, but the moſt ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of all Creatures, to be thus terrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at nothing, and ſcar'd with ſuch an imaginary Bugbear of his own making: All other Beings have ſome real Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of their fears; and ſurely Man muſt be the ſillieſt of all Creatures, to be thus haunted with the dread of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:106946:19"/> inviſible Powers and a Judgment to come, if no ſuch things were to be fear'd or expected: his Underſtanding and Reaſon would ſerve him to good purpoſe, to ſuggeſt ſuch needleſs ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, as to fright him with a Dream, and make him tremble at his own Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow. So that this remorſe and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of mind, with which the greateſt Sinners are purſued, is a plain Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a Deity, without which no tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable account could be given of theſe things.</p>
            <p>But if Conſcience be ſo clear a proof and witneſs of a Deity, how comes it to paſs, that ſo many deny and forget God, when they have ſuch a faithful and conſtant Monitor within to keep him in remembrance? why the Miſery as well as Myſtery of it is, that too many ſilence the Voice of Conſcience, and will not ſuffer it to ſpeak, or if (as it ſometimes happens) they cannot ſtop its mouth, like the deaf Adder they ſtop their ear, <hi>and refuſe to hear the Voice of the Charmer, tho he charm never ſo wiſely;</hi> yea, tho they are many times hard put to it to ſtill the clamour and importunity of their own Minds, yet they uſe all their Arts to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:106946:20"/> keep it quiet, and to ſtifle thoſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victions.</p>
            <p>But what courſe do they take to effect it? Why,</p>
            <p>Sometimes by lulling it a-ſleep in a carnal ſecurity; or elſe, if that will not do, by hardening and ſearing it as with a hot Iron.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I ſay, ſome men to keep their Conſcience quiet, endeavour to lull it a-ſleep in a carnal and fatal ſecurity; and this they do by an inordinate pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit of their ſenſual Luſts and Pleaſures; if the ſerious thoughts of a God ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times preſs too much upon them, they ſeek either to drown them in their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperate Cups, or to ſtifle them by the ſoftneſs of Lewdneſs and Dalliance: If they find their minds begin to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver out of this Lethargy, and theſe ſerious thoughts return, they have recourſe to idle and looſe Company to relieve themſelves from the trouble of them, where they keep their Heads ſo hot with their frequent exceſſes, that they are ſeldom or never cool enough to conſider things as they ought, and thus by bringing a continual doozineſs up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Senſes, they paſs away their time as in a Dream or Slumber, and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:106946:20"/> by degrees fall into an utter forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of God and their Duty. But if they cannot preſently thus lull their Conſcience a-ſleep, they endeavour,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly.</hi> To harden it againſt Convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to ſear it as with an hot Iron; and this they do by vicious habits con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted by a long continued cuſtom in Sin, whereby the Mind is in a manner ſtupified, and made ſenſeleſs of all Evil and Danger: This is ſuch a degree of wickedneſs to which none can arrive preſently, for <hi>Nemo repente fuit Turpiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</hi> Time is requir'd to wear off the impreſſions of Good and Evil; for Conſcience recoils at firſt, and hath that natural tenderneſs, as to feel the ſmart, and fear the evil of ſuch courſes; till by frequent reſiſting its Calls, they have overcome this Reluctance, and made it become callous and paſt feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and thus by a long practice and continuance in Sin, they gradually loſe the ſenſe and awe of a Deity, and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle in Atheiſm and Infidelity.</p>
            <p>Now for Men to be at ſo great pains to ſtupifie their Conſcience, and hinder it from doing its office, muſt be a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry unwiſe and unſafe courſe; for this is to ſilence the Voice of God within us,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:106946:21"/> and to turn the deaf Ear to our Maker; yea 'tis to deſpiſe the remembrance, and hate the knowledge of him, and to ſay with them in <hi>Job, depart from us, we deſire not the knowledge of thy ways.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet after all their pains, this will prove in the end but a fruitleſs at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, for Conſcience will one time or other ſpeak, and loud enough to be heard too, and tho it may be lull'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep a while, it will e're long awake, and ring a Peal of Vengeance in the Ears of all ſuch bold and daring Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, as ſeek now to ſtupifie and ſilence it.</p>
            <p>Indeed, that preſent ſenſeleſſneſs and ſtupidity, which they bring upon their mind, ſerves but to render their condition the more deſperate and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medileſs; for as in bodily diſtempers, when the ſenſe of pain is loſt, the Patient is in greateſt danger, and the diſeaſe proves moſt mortal, and incu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable; even ſo in ſpiritual Maladies, when the mind is paſt feeling, the Caſe is commonly paſt recovery; and evermore the leſs ſenſe of pain, the greater danger: which ſhould teach us to <hi>hearken to the voice of God</hi> and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:106946:21"/> Conſcience <hi>whilſt it's call'd to day, leſt the Heart be hardened through the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfulneſs of Sin;</hi> before the Mind grow brawny and inſenſible, and fall into ſuch a deep ſleep, as nothing but Eternal Miſery can awake it.</p>
            <p>In a word, the peace and tranqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity that the Mind feels from the Apprehenſions of a God, ſhews it to be the intereſt of Mankind to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and pleaſe him, which alone can give us this hearts-eaſe: And likewiſe the terrors and frightful Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions, that flow from a diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute life, are ſufficient to make all Men abhor and abandon the Cauſe of Atheiſm. I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>
                  <hi>SIR,</hi> 
               </salute>
               <signed>Your Faithful Friend, A. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="letter">
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:106946:22"/>
            <head>LETTER IV.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Find you ſenſible of the hard ſhifts the Atheiſt is put to, to ſilence the Voice of Conſcience, and ſtifle the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larms and Convictions of his own mind, together with the Folly and Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of that Stratagem. I proceed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to another, and that is to aſcribe the Notion of a Deity to a too great eaſineſs of Belief, or a fond Credulity: This we find to be a frequent Plea and Objection in this caſe. One great Argument for the proof of a God, is taken from the Univerſal Conſent and Agreement of Mankind in this Belief, there being nothing ſo generally own'd and receiv'd, in all times and places, as this Truth; and that not only a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Wiſe and Knowing, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven among the rudeſt and moſt ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant part of the World: <hi>Nulla gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam barbara,</hi> &amp;c. ſaith the <hi>Roman</hi> Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:106946:22"/> There is no Nation ſo barbarous as not to Believe and Worſhip a God.</p>
            <p>Now whence ſhould this Univerſal Conſent of Mankind in this Belief pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, but from the Voice of Nature, which ſpeaks loud enough to be heard, the ſound whereof is gone through the Earth, and the Words to the end of the World? Yea, this can be no other than an Impreſſion ſtamp'd on the Mind, by a Divine Hand, engraven by the Finger of God himſelf, and interwoven into the very Frame of our Being.</p>
            <p>But how doth the Atheiſt evade this univerſally receiv'd Truth? Why, by charging Mankind with too great a Credulity in this matter; as if all Men beſide himſelf, were too haſty and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of belief, and took up this perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion upon very ſlender and inſufficient grounds; whereas he ſcorns to be thus eaſily led by vain talk, and to yield up his underſtanding to uncertain ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour: Hence the great Atheiſt of our Age founds all Religion upon the belief of tales publickly told, as if the Being and belief of a Deity, were built only upon a report handed down from one
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:106946:23"/> to another, and had no better foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on than common Fame.</p>
            <p>Now is not this a ſtrange piece of raſhneſs and preſumption, for any to condemn all before or beſide himſelf, for a company of credulous Fools and Children, that can believe any thing, and ſwallow the greateſt difficulties, without the leaſt reaſon or examination. But let us enquire a little farther into this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>Who was it that firſt rais'd this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of a Deity? Or by whom was this Tradition began? This is matter well worth the enquiry, who made this firſt Diſcovery, or rais'd this Spirit, which all the Wiſdom of the world could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver conjure down ſince. Certainly he muſt have been ſome wiſe or cunning Body, that could invent and propagate ſo plauſible a ſtory, as to paſs the Tryal of all Ages, and that none could ever find out or detect the falſhood of it, ſure the Fame of ſuch a perſon would have been Recorded in the Annals of Time, and Poſterity could never have been ſo unjuſt to his Memory, as to let him ſink away in ſilence and oblivion: And yet the Atheiſt here is wholly at a loſs in theſe things, and will neither pretend
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:106946:23"/> to tell us the time when, the place where, or the perſon by whom this report firſt began: Only (as one hath obſerv'd) he thinks it probable that ſome body long ago (he knows not when) beyond the Memory of all Ages, did ſtart ſuch a notion in the World, and that it hath paſt for currant ever ſince; but if this Tradition be older than all Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, why may it not have been from the beginning? And then it will be far more probable, to be a notion which was bred in the mind of Man, and born with him, than a Tradition tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted from hand to hand through all Generations, eſpecially being found in thoſe barbarous Nations, that have ſcarce a Tradition of any thing elſe. But how come theſe Men thus to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the general Senſe of Mankind, and to call in queſtion ſo univerſally own'd and receiv'd a Truth? Why! this proceeds,</p>
            <p>Partly from their great unwilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to believe it, which makes them take hold of any, even the meaneſt ſhifts, to countenance their unbelief. And</p>
            <p>Partly from an Affectation of Singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity, whereby they would be thought
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:106946:24"/> wiſer and more knowing, than any that went before them, that they ſee farther into matters than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Men, and that their Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings are by head and ſhoulders taller than their Brethren; they know well enough, that ſhould they go on with the common herd, and ſay and do as others that have gone before them, they ſhould be thought to be no wiſer than they; and therefore that they may ſet up for Wits, and be accounted Men of a deeper reach and inſight into things, than others, they ſtrike out of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon road, and go a new untrodden way by themſelves; this makes them look upon the belief of a Deity, (tho' con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd by the general conſent of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind) to be only the effect of weakneſs and want of judgment, that they who entertain it, are merely carried away with the Stream, and like eaſie cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulous perſons, take up things upon truſt, from the uncertain Hear-ſay and Report of others no wiſer than themſelves: Whereas they, like Men of judgment, believe and act by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Rule; and where their own Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon cannot convince them of a truth, there no Authority of others ſhall ſway
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:106946:24"/> them to the belief of it. And thus by a vain conceit and affectation of Singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity, they leave the track in which all others have gone before them, which unawares bewilders and leads them into Atheiſm.</p>
            <p>But is it a vain Credulity, to embrace a Truth confirm'd by the Conſent and Approbation of all Mankind? or is it any piece of Wiſdom, to ſet up a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle opinion againſt the Wiſdom of the whole World? No, far from it; the wiſeſt of Men hath told us, that he that is wiſe in his own conceit is a fool; and certainly he muſt be extremely ſo, that thinks himſelf wiſer than all Men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide him: Indeed, to keep the mind from being enſlav'd to precarious and Vulgar Notions, or receiving things up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on truſt without examination, is to aſſert the freedom of the Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which very well becomes a wiſe Man to do; but to reject an Opinion merely becauſe it hath been univerſally receiv'd, is a rudeneſs offer'd to the Reaſon of Mankind; for if many heads may be ſuppos'd to be wiſer than one, that wherein all Heads concenter and agree, ought in Reaſon to be preferr'd before any ſingle opinion; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:106946:25"/> to quarrel with a Truth, for no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſon, but becauſe it hath been own'd and embrac'd by all, is an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardonable piece of pride and ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity; for this makes Men overvalue themſelves, and ſet too low a price upon the judgment of their betters, which is a high piece of arrogance and folly: Yea by this means they deprive them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of the benefit and aſſiſtance of other Mens Underſtandings, and lean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wholly upon their own, are thereby often betray'd into great errors and miſcarriages.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, we are forbid to <hi>follow a multitude in doing Evil,</hi> but not in receiving Truth, which is the greateſt good we can do to our ſelves or others: And tho' we are bid <hi>to try all things,</hi> yet we are requir'd <hi>to hold faſt that which is good,</hi> and not to ſtart aſide from the belief of that which hath paſt the tryal and approbation of all Times and Ages.</p>
            <p>There is (as one hath well obſerv'd) a Reverence due to the Judgment of Mankind, and that which hath been receiv'd by all or moſt Men, hath been ever thought moſt worthy of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation:
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:106946:25"/> yea the laws of modeſty re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire us to think others better than our ſelves, and to ſuſpect our own Judgment, when it croſſes theirs; for tho' the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of Men may be ſometimes miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, which ſhould therefore put us up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſtricter ſearch and enquiry into Truth, yet to be over poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and confident againſt the univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Senſe and Belief of Mankind, is to reſiſt the cleareſt evidence we can have, and to run counter to the greateſt proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities.</p>
            <p>But what if theſe great Maſters of Wit ſhould all this while be found the moſt Credulous and eaſie of belief of all Men? what then will become of all theſe vain Boaſts and Pretenſions to Reaſon? And yet this is as clear as the Sun at Noon-day; for they believe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things without the leaſt colour and ſhadow of reaſon; and deny others that have all poſſible evidence of truth; both which are apparent inſtances of a groſs and abſurd Credulity.</p>
            <p>They believe that there is no God, and conſequently that 'tis impoſſible there ſhould be one, a thing which no Art of Man ever could or pretended to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:106946:26"/>
            <p>Again, they believe either that the World was never made, or if it were, that 'twas made by chance, and that all things in it came into that excellent or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der they now are, by mere fortune: which ſhews that they can believe at random, and take up the moſt abſurd <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> at a venture. Again,</p>
            <p>They believe that tho' matter be in it ſelf a dull and ſenſeleſs thing, utterly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of Reaſon and Underſtanding, yet there can be no ſpiritual or immate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Being to influence or actuate it. In a Word,</p>
            <p>The Atheiſt can believe againſt all the Senſe and Reaſon of all Mankind, and think all the World beſide himſelf to conſiſt only of Fools and Knaves; a bold <hi>Brittain!</hi> And yet thoſe and many other are the goodly Articles of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſt's <hi>Creed,</hi> which he that can ſwallow, muſt be a man of ſtrong Faith or vaſt Credulity, and muſt believe with his Will, not with his Underſtanding. I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>
                  <hi>SIR,</hi> 
               </salute>
               <signed>Yours, A. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="letter">
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:106946:26"/>
            <head>LETTER V.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>ANother Device of the Atheiſt is to reſolve the Belief of a God into the Principles and Prejudices of Education: This Device is near a-kin to and grounded upon the former, and pretends to give ſome account of the ſpring and riſe of this Credulity; which he takes to be from the firſt impreſſions of Education; this being the firſt Notion inſtill'd by Parents into their Children, as ſoon as they come to underſtand any thing, and is improv'd by thoſe who have the Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and Management of them ever after.</p>
            <p>And here they obſerve, what deep impreſſions are made upon the Mind, by the firſt things we hear or learn; how long they are wont to continue with us, and how ready Men are to communicate them to one another, and more eſpecially to derive them to
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:106946:27"/> their offspring: From whence they think ſuch a general belief of a Deity may eaſily be ſuppos'd in time to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and be tranſmitted down from hand to hand through all Generations.</p>
            <p>Now here the Queſtion may be ask'd again, Who was the firſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that invented and convey'd down this Notion? what was his name or his Son's name, that we may know him? how came he to entertain it himſelf? who taught it him? and how came he ſo readily to believe and propagate it to Poſterity? Why, of all this the Atheiſt can give no man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of account, unleſs he will flye to the Holy Scripture, and ſay, that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> the firſt Man had it from God, and taught it to his Children, and ſo convey'd it down to all Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; but this would be to yield up the Cauſe, and to acknowledge a firſt Being and Maker of all things, which yet he is very unwilling to grant.</p>
            <p>Beſides, that this is a precarious and groundleſs Hypotheſis, may plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear from this, that Men in all Ages have been known to be of different tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, and to have had various and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent ways and methods of Educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:106946:27"/> by which means they have receiv'd different Impreſſions, and entertain'd various Sentiments of things: And yet we find all Men, in all times, and of all tempers (tho' differing never ſo much in other things) to agree and concenter in this belief of a God, which ſhews it to have another and higher Principle than that of Education.</p>
            <p>Again, if we conſult the frame and make of our Being, we ſhall find this Notion of a Deity ſtampt upon our very Natures, and that in ſuch plain and legible Characters, as may eaſily ſhew whoſe workmanſhip we are, and out of what hands we came; and this too in perſons of no Education, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any thing was inſtill'd into them by it, which farther proves it to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from a higher Cauſe: To all which if we add moreover,</p>
            <p>That ſtrong and powerful Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that is found in all Men to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip a God, we ſhall find this to go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and not to be planted in them by Education: If we ſurvey the World, we may obſerve a natural proneneſs and propenſity to Religion, even in the moſt barbarous and uncultivated parts of it; all of them every where conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:106946:28"/> together to worſhip ſomething or other as a God: Now this cannot poſſibly be owing only to Educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which may indeed direct, but can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not infuſe theſe Inclinations; he that created the Soul, could alone put that byaſs into it, that draws ſo ſtrong to the adoration of him; for the beſt nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture can no more put ſuch new Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, than it can put a new Nature into us: So that this univerſal Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to religious Worſhip muſt proceed from ſomething within, that is born with us, and is connatural to our Being; and can no more flow from any thing imprinted on our Minds from without, than the natural Paſſions of Hope and Fear are owing to the impreſſions of outward Objects.</p>
            <p>But here the Atheiſt tells us, That this Argument taken from an univerſal Inclination to worſhip a Deity, will hold as ſtrong for Polytheiſm and Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, as for a Unity of the Godhead; there being as great, if not a greater part of the World led by it to worſhip many falſe Gods than one true one.</p>
            <p>Now to this, which is all the Atheiſt hath to ſay in this caſe, ſundry anſwers may be given. As,</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:106946:28"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Aſſertion on which the Objection is grounded is a great mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, for the greateſt and wiſeſt part of Mankind have ever paid their Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations to one Supreme Being: As for the Jewiſh Nation, the whole body of them ſerv'd one only God, known by the name <hi>Jehovah,</hi> as is evident from Prophane as well as Sacred Hiſtory; and for the other Nations, that deriv'd their Pedigree and Tradition from them, they had always one above the reſt whom they worſhipp'd with the higheſt acts of Adoration: Indeed ſome of the groſſer Heathens multiplied their Gods, according to the multitude and variety of Bleſſings they ſuppos'd to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive from them; but theſe were deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Philoſophers and more knowing Men, and the practice of the Multitude without the opinion and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of the Wiſe, ſignifies no more (as one hath told us in this caſe) than many Cyphers without a Figure.</p>
            <p>Again, <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Polytheiſm of the Heathens is a good argument a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Atheiſm, and their Idolatries are a plain proof of a Deity; for the rudeſt and moſt ignorant of all people have had thoſe impreſſions of him upon
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:106946:29"/> their Mind, that they would rather have many Gods than be without any, and worſhip falſe Gods rather than none at all. Tho' they miſtook the true God, yet they all agreed in this, to worſhip ſome God or other; and this miſtake of theirs was not for want of ſufficient Evidence, but from the neglect or abuſe of their natural Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, which led them from the true to falſe Gods, for <hi>when they knew God (ſaith the Apoſtle) they worſhipped him not as God, and therefore their fooliſh hearts were darkened.</hi> Moreover,</p>
            <p>Laſtly, the many falſe Gods of the Heathen are a plain proof that there is one true one, for all Counterfeits ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a Reality; there would be no falſe Coin, if there were none true; all Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges are intended to repreſent ſomething that is real; neither would any Idols be ſet up, if there were not a true God to be worſhipped. In ſhort then, the Notion of a Deity muſt be founded in Nature, becauſe 'tis univerſal; and could not be acquired by Education, it being found in thoſe that never had any.</p>
            <p>Beſide, nothing is laſting but what is natural; for the beſt things acquir'd
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:106946:29"/> by Inſtruction, have in many perſons been loſt and forgotten; and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the Notion of a God would have fail'd in time, and the Worſhip of him ceas'd in many places, if it had no firmer Principle.</p>
            <p>Seeing then that both theſe have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued through all Times and Ages, and are ſtill found in all Perſons and Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, yea, ſince the Atheiſt himſelf can ſcarce wear off the Impreſſion, or rid his Mind of the awe and ſenſe of a Deity, 'tis a poor ſhift to reſolve the Belief and Worſhip of him into the Principles and Prejudices of Educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>
                  <hi>SIR,</hi> 
               </salute>
               <signed>Yours, A. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="letter">
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:106946:30"/>
            <head>LETTER VI.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Shew'd in my laſt, That the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of Education could not create, but muſt ſuppoſe a Deity, and that the knowledge and belief we have of him, is owing not ſo much to the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Inſtructions we learn from others, as the inward Inclinations implanted in our own Mind; which are not taught, but born with us.</p>
            <p>But if the Atheiſt cannot ſolve this great Phaenomenon, or account for ſo general a Credulity this way, he hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Device for that purpoſe; and that is to aſcribe the belief and worſhip of a God to <hi>Fear,</hi> or a ſuperſtitious dread of ſome inviſible Powers: And this he thinks cannot fail to do it. For the mind of Man (he tells us) and of ſome eſpecially, is mightily ſubject to the impreſſions of Fear, which are wont to ſink deep and continue long with them; and theſe again are apt to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>print
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:106946:30"/> the ſame dread on the Minds of others; which being diſcover'd and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated, fill melancholy heads with infinite Fears and Jealouſies, which at length increaſe into a general awe and dread of ſuch a Being: ſo that Men are frighted into this belief by the fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent talk of a God, as Children are into the fear of Spirits by the Tales of Faries and Hobgoblins; and for this they quote that noted ſaying of the Poet,</p>
            <q>Primus in Orbe Deos fecit Timor.</q>
            <p>Fear firſt made Gods: Men being ſcar'd with ſome Jealouſies ariſing in their Minds about it, and terrified with the thoughts of what might hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen.</p>
            <p>Now here by this Aſſertion, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſt grants that the Minds of Men are generally ſeiz'd and poſſeſs'd with the Fears and Apprehenſions of a God, which is too well known and felt, to be call'd in queſtion: So that the main enquiry here is, whether Fear can create this Being; or whether ſuch a Being may not rather create theſe Fears? for ſince all other Paſſions pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſe
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:106946:31"/> their Object, it is not to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd how fear alone ſhould make it; if there be a God, that preſides over all things, and inſpects our ways, there is great reaſon to fear him; but if there be none, 'tis not to be imagin'd, how fear ſhould make ſuch a Being, or cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate ſuch an univerſal Belief in Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, that there is one. But how come ſo many to fear, where no fear is? what makes Men indow'd with Reaſon thus to be ſcar'd with their own ſhadow? or if ſome ſuch timerous crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures may be found, that are apt to be frighted with the terrors of their own fancy, How come all Mankind to be ſeiz'd with theſe panick fears? what ſhould create ſuch an univerſal trembling? or rivet this frightful Idea ſo deep into Mens Minds, that no Art or Endeavours can root it out?</p>
            <p>Why, of this no account can be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven without a Deity? which might well enough imprint this dread upon them, from a ſenſe of his infinite Power and Greatneſs.</p>
            <p>Indeed, 'tis eaſie to conceive how Infinite Power and Juſtice may cauſe a dread; but 'tis not to be imagin'd,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:106946:31"/> how dread ſhould be the cauſe of ſuch infinite perfections.</p>
            <p>Again, it may be asked whether this Fear were before or after a Deity? if it be affirm'd to be before, as it muſt be, if Fear be the Cauſe of him, the Cauſe being ever before the Effect; it will follow, that ſomething may be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that which is Eternal; for ſince the Notion of a God implies a Being that exiſted from all Eternity, if Fear preceeded, and made this Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, it muſt have been before Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and likewiſe give a Being to that, which never had or could have any beginning; both which are mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt contradictions.</p>
            <p>If this Fear be ſaid to be after a Deity, then it could not be the Cauſe of him; foraſmuch as no Effect can be before, but muſt ſtill come after the Cauſe.</p>
            <p>Whence then ſhould this fear proceed, by which Men are aw'd into this Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief? Why, it muſt proceed either from the ſuggeſtions and report of others, or from the inward ſuggeſtions of our own Mind.</p>
            <p>If it came from the Relation and ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions of others, it may be ask'd, who ſuggeſted it to them? And this enquiry will
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:106946:32"/> not ceaſe, till it be trac'd up to the firſt Author; in which the Atheiſt is at the ſame loſs as he was before, in running up the riſe of this Tradition.</p>
            <p>If theſe Fears proceed from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſuggeſtions of our own Mind, which is apt to fancy terrible things; it may be ask'd, who or what is it that brings to mind thoſe terrible things, and occaſions thoſe ſuggeſtions? Why this can be nothing but the ſenſe of ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible Powers, whom we have ſome way or other offended, which may cauſe ſome remorſe, and imprint ſome fears of his diſpleaſure: And let the Atheiſt give any other account of it, if he can.</p>
            <p>Beſide, does not the Notion of a God imply a Being of infinite Mercy and Goodneſs, that is always ready to take care of, to ſupport and comfort his Creatures? And ſince the Object of Fear is always ſomething that is dreadful, how can Fear create the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of ſuch a Being, which is rather the Object of deſire than dread, and deſerves muchmore to be lov'd and wiſh'd for, than to be fear'd by us? So that fear alone, could never produce this Noble Effect; it might indeed beget an opinion of ſome ſtern, ſour, and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:106946:32"/> ſevere Being, to be dreaded and ſhun'd by all that hear of him; but could never form a Notion of a Gracious, Merciful, and tender-hearted Lord, that is to be lov'd and deſir'd by all that know him: And therefore the Atheiſt to make his <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> the more plauſible, muſt join Love and Hope to Fear, to compleat this Glorious and Divine Atchievement.</p>
            <p>Moreover, the Love of ſo benign, gracious, and amiable a Being, is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to overcome and expel fear, and nothing but the ſollicitation of ſenſual Luſts, could keep Mankind from admiring and doteing upon him: <hi>There is no fear in love, but perfect love caſteth out fear; becauſe fear hath torment, he that feareth is not made perfect in love:</hi> 1 John 4. 18.</p>
            <p>Indeed the Love and Relation we bear to a bountiful Creator may well enough admit of a filial fear, conſiſting in an unwillingneſs to offend or diſpleaſe him; but no ſervile tormenting fear can conſiſt with the love that is due to ſo excellent a Being.</p>
            <p>So that Fear is ſo far from making a God, that it tends rather (if it were poſſible) to unmake him, to turn him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:106946:33"/> Tyrant, and conſequently to make him the object of our hatred and aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation; for he that hath ſuch dreadful Apprehenſions, cannot but wiſh there were no God, and from thence is but one remove from believing there is none. Yea,</p>
            <p>This ſlaviſh fear tends to bebaſe Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, and even to unmake him too, by degrading him to a lower Species, for <hi>Degeneres animos Timor Arguit.</hi> Such a fear ſinks him beneath the dignity of his Nature, and makes him like the Beaſt that periſheth. Furthermore,</p>
            <p>If there were no Being of ſuch infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Perfections to employ our Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation, the higheſt and nobleſt faculties of the Soul would be vain and uſeleſs; the Underſtanding would want an Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject ſuitable to the Capacity of its Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion; the Will would have none commenſurate to the largeneſs of its deſires; the Affections would be deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of an object worthy of its Love and Complacence; yea Fear it ſelf would want both an Object and a Reaſon for thoſe frequent terrors, that haunt and aſſault the Mind. Now there being no Power or Faculty in the meaneſt Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but what there is ſome Reaſon
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:106946:33"/> and Uſe for, can it be conceiv'd that the Nobleſt Faculties of the Soul ſhould be planted in it in vain, and become all uſeleſs for want of a ſuitable Object to employ them.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, if there were no God, Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind would have nothing but temporal good things to deſire, and nothing but temporal Evils to fear; of both which the brute Beaſts have a quicker ſenſe than he: Yea his Reaſon, which is the Perfection and Glory of Humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, would ſerve for no other end, but to be a Caterer to the Senſes, and provide for the gratification of a Carnal Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite, which may be as well if not better gratified without than with it: So that without a Deity, as all Fear would be in vain, ſo all the ſuperior Faculties of the Soul, <hi>viz.</hi> Underſtanding and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, would be uſeleſs and inſignificant, as having no Object fit to exerciſe or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain them. I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>
                  <hi>SIR,</hi> 
               </salute>
               <signed>Yours, A. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="letter">
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:106946:34"/>
            <head>LETTER VII.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Find you ſenſible in your laſt, that Fear could not be the Cauſe, but the Effect and Conſequent of a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of a Deity; and that no tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Reaſon can be given of the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral fear and dread of a God, if there were no ſuch Being: So that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſt being beaten out of this Subter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge; I proceed in this to</p>
            <p>Another Device, which he ſeeks to take ſhelter in, and that is, to aſcribe the Notion of a Deity, to State-policy, and to make the Belief of it a Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of cunning Men, to keep the World in awe.</p>
            <p>This is a new Device invented and propagated by ſome in this latter Age, who (as a great Man hath told us) i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine that ſome great Prince or Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litician, like <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> ſet up this image of a Deity, and commanded <hi>all People and Nations to fall down and
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:106946:34"/> Worſhip it:</hi> And this being found an uſeful Engine of State, to keep Men in obedience to Government, hath been receiv'd by all Princes and States ever ſince. A goodly device indeed! and no doubt the iſſue of ſome wiſe and politick Head-piece; and to make it the more plauſible; they inſiſt at large, upon the Reaſon why it ſhould be che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh'd and countenanc'd by all Princes, <hi>viz.</hi> Becauſe of the good influence it hath upon the awing the People into O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience. Again,</p>
            <p>They tell us of the Peoples readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to comply with the humours and practices of Princes, who giving their Example and Encouragement herein, are eaſily followed and imitated by their Subjects: by which means this Notion, having the Stamp of Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty upon it, hath paſs'd current, and is generally embrac'd and kept up in the World: This is the ſumm of what they have to ſay in this Matter. Now here we may obſerve,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That this Device plainly ſuppoſes the Uſefulneſs of Religion. towards the Peace and Welfare of Mankind, and how greatly it conduces to the good Order and Government of the World;
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:106946:35"/> which ſhews it to be the intereſt of Mankind to wiſh it true; and this (one would think) ſhould rather incline Men to embrace, than evade ſo uſeful a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>But by whom was this Engine of State devis'd? where or when did this great Prince or Politician live, that firſt found out this <hi>Arcanum imperii,</hi> this great Secret or Myſtery of Government? what proof is there alledg'd for any ſuch Contrivance? Why, none at all; no diſcovery hath been yet made of the Author of this Invention; it ſtill remains a Myſtery, as well as an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine of State, a Cobweb ſpun out of ſome fanciful and ſubtle Brain; in a Word, tis a mere Conjecture, taken up without the leaſt appearance of Reaſon, or proof for any part of it.</p>
            <p>Indeed, The thing appears in it ſelf unpracticable; for how is it poſſible for the wiſeſt Politician to rivet ſuch a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into the Minds of all Men, that ſhould never get out? where is the Perſon that ever did ſuch a feat? and if no ſuch one be any where to be found, we may ſafely conclude the deep
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:106946:35"/> and laſting impreſſions of a Deity up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Mens Minds, to proceed not from the Art of Man, but from the Finger of God.</p>
            <p>Beſide, this is an improbable way of compaſſing the deſign; for the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleſt Politicians are wont to work up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the inclinations they find planted in Mens Nature; but do not hope to put new ones into them: They are wiſe enough to know, that Men are more eaſily led, than driven; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore chuſe rather to make uſe of thoſe Principles they find them already poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs'd of, than go about to infuſe new. Hence it comes to paſs, that Princes reap the benefits of Peace and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der from Principles they never ſowed in the hearts of their Subjects, but found planted there; and 'tis moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that the People are much more aw'd and kept to their duty, by the natural impreſſions of Religion, than by any artificial Methods of Policy or Contrivance: So that Politicians promote their ends, not by making but finding Religion in the Minds of Men; for tho' Reaſon of State may cheriſh, it can never create the Notion of a Deity.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:106946:36"/>
            <p>But have Princes or Politicians been more free from the Fears of a Deity, or the Terrors of another World, than other Men? This would be, if Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion were only a Device or Engine of State: whereas we ſee and find the quite contrary, for they have the ſame ſenſe and impreſſions of theſe things with other Men, and can no more rid their Minds of them, than the meaneſt of their Subjects: Hiſtory tells us, how ſome of the <hi>Roman</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors were wont to be frighted with the noiſe of Thunder; as thinking it to be the voice of God: We read how <hi>Caligula</hi> us'd to creep under a Bed at the ſound of it, taking it for a ſign of the anger and diſpleaſure of Heaven; and we read of many other great Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and States-men, who have been alarm'd with the fears of a God, and the terrors of another World: Now if Religion were only a Juggle of State, or a politick Device of cunning Men; how come they to be thus terrified with their own Contrivance? Men are not wont to be affrighted with Bugbears of their own making, or to tremble at that which they know
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:106946:36"/> to be a mere ſcarecrow; 'tis plain, the greateſt and wiſeſt perſons that have ever been, have known of no ſuch Cheat in Religion, for if they had, no account could be given of thoſe fears and troubles of Conſcience, which they in all Ages had about it.</p>
            <p>Beſide, 'tis hard to conceive, how all the Princes and Potentates of the Earth ſhould agree together to entertain a Fiction; and tho' they have ſuch diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Deſigns and Intereſts, ſhould yet conſpire to deviſe and promote a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that is void of all Reaſon or Truth.</p>
            <p>Or if they could, how is it to be i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magin'd, that the People ſhould be all ſo ready to receive it? They are not wont ſo eaſily to believe their Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours upon their bare Word, or em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace a Notion that hath ſo plain a deſign upon their Peace and Welfare: Yea the more ſubtle and politick they take their Governours to be, the more they are apt to ſuſpect them; and to pry into the Reaſons of their Counſels and Intentions.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, if the Notion of a God were only a politick Contrivance to keep the World in awe, or a Device fram'd in
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:106946:37"/> ſome Mens heads, to cozen others in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to obedience to them, how comes it to paſs, that this was never diſcover'd in any Age? Sure it would have been found out one time or other; Cheats do not always continue undiſcover'd; Truth commonly breaks out, and Time lays open the Impoſture: if then this pretended Secret was never known or diſcover'd by any, but remains ſtill as much a Secret as ever, we may ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well conclude it to be it ſelf a Juggle and Fiction of ſome Mens brain; or a Device of the Atheiſt to cozen and deceive himſelf. I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Yours, A. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="letter">
            <head>LETTER VIII.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHen the Atheiſt is driven out of the Refuge of State-policy, and can neither tell the perſon by whom, or the time when this Engine of State was invented, He flies to</p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:106946:37"/>
            <p>Another Device, which is to reſolve the Notion and Belief of a God into com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Compact: An account whereof is briefly this.</p>
            <p>That Mankind, for the better preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Human Society, by common Conſent form'd this Notion of a God, which they generally agreed together to embrace; and finding the benefit and good influence of it upon the publick welfare, have by common Compact preſerv'd and kept it up ever ſince: A notable Account indeed! which ſhews that ſome Men will believe any thing, rather than what they ſhould.</p>
            <p>However this account farther grants the Uſefulneſs of Religion to the welfare of Human Society, which is indeed ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to it, that 'tis impoſſible it ſhould long ſubſiſt or continue without it; for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is the Bond or Cement that holds all the parts of it together, and gives all the force and efficacy to the Laws by which 'tis upheld: All the Obligations of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which alone can keep Men to their duty, reſult from the Belief of a God; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which, no ties of Oaths, Promiſes, or Engagements, could hold Men either to Honeſty or Obedience: So that the uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs and neceſſity of this Notion to the welfare of Mankind, ſhould methinks en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:106946:38"/> all Men to entertain it, to wiſh it true, and to give all the ſtrength that may be to the Arguments brought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm it; for he that endeavours to evade this Truth, is an Enemy not only to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but to the Happineſs and Tranquili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Human Society, and does what in him lies to deſtroy the Peace and Welfare of Mankind.</p>
            <p>But when and where was this general Meeting of Mankind, in which they form'd this Notion of a Deity, and enter'd into this ſolemn Compact to Believe and propagate it? Who ſummon'd or call'd them together from all the remote parts of the World? Or did they happen lucki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to come and meet together by Chance? Sure, ſome Hiſtory or other of the World would have Recorded this grand Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of Mankind for this purpoſe, which, if it ever were, was one of the moſt memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable things that hath been ever acted in it. But ſince no account hath been ever given of ſuch a Meeting, we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude it to be a meer figment, to be met with no where but in an Atheiſtical brain.</p>
            <p>But if the Atheiſt could get over this difficulty, which is indeed inſuperable, there are many other in this unaccounta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Compact, in which he muſt be unavoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dably intangl'd; for how came all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:106946:38"/> of all places and Countries, ſo unanimouſly to jump and agree together in this Notion? When there is ſcarce any little Town or City, where ſuch an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire Agreement is to be found in matters of opinion, how incredible is it that all the People in the World, of the moſt diſtant Places, and the moſt different Humours, Intereſts, and Inclinations, ſhould all agree together in framing this Notion, and ſo univerſally conſpire in the Belief of it?</p>
            <p>Beſide, how came this Notion fram'd by them, to be ſo generally receiv'd by all Poſterity ever ſince? was this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and Compact of theirs ſo made, as to bind all their Heirs and Succeſſors for ever? Or how come all Generations ſo readily to take themſelves to be bound by it? eſpecially when no Inſtrument or Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence can be produc'd, when and where this Argreement was ratified; certainly, this is more than was ever known of any other Compact or Agreement either be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore or ſince.</p>
            <p>Moreover, are there not ſome Places and Perſons ſo rude, as to be without any Commerce or Correſpondence with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Nations? And how came they to hear of this Compact, or to think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves bound by it? Sure, they muſt be mighty credulous, who can receive a
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:106946:39"/> matter of ſo great importance upon ſuch ſlender Evidence, and take themſelves to be oblig'd by a Contract which they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard of; eſpecially in a thing that ſits ſo uneaſie upon the Minds of many, whoſe intereſt and wiſh it is that it were not true: For are there not ſome very deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to rid themſelves of the diſquieting Fear and Belief of a God? do not too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny labour hard to caſt off this Check, which tends ſo much to reſtrain their Luſts, and abridge their Pleaſures? And if this Belief depended only on ſuch a precarious Contract, contriv'd and made they know not where, or by whom, would they not ſoon find a way to get out of it?</p>
            <p>Theſe and many other abſurdities at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend this Device, which he that can ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, may be indeed a Man of little Faith, but of vaſt Credulity; he muſt ceaſe to blame any for eaſineſs of Belief, that can give his aſſent upon ſuch ſlender grounds; and if the Atheiſt can build his Confidence upon no better Foundation, he muſt no longer ſet up for a Man of Wit or Reaſon, nor pretend to any other demonſtration, but that of his own folly.</p>
            <p>How much more rational is it, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the Notion of a Deity to be a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of Divine infuſion, than an Article of Human Contract? and the Belief of it
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:106946:39"/> to be rather founded in Nature than built upon Artifice and Agreement? Is it likely that the Idea of a Being abſolutely perfect, infinitely wiſe, juſt, and gracious, the Omnipotent and glorious Maker and Preſerver of all things, ſhould be merely fram'd by Compact? or that the whole World ſhould univerſally agree to profeſs and worſhip ſuch a Being, if there were no ſuch thing? Is not this at once to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe upon the Reaſon of Mankind, and to reflect upon the Honour of our Maker, to make him a Creature of our own Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and the Effect of Human Contrivance? There is no Compact but what may be and hath in time been laid aſide; and if this Belief neither hath nor can be totally e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras'd, it owes its riſe to a higher Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and muſt be more deeply rooted in the Minds of Men. I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>
                  <hi>SIR,</hi> 
               </salute>
               <signed>Yours, A. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="letter">
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:106946:40"/>
            <head>LETTER IX.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAving ſhew'd the vanity of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſt's Pleas in accounting for the Univerſal Tradition and Conſent of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind in the Belief of a God, if there were no ſuch Being;</p>
            <p>I come now to another Device, made uſe of to rid their Minds of him; and that is to deny the Notion and Being of a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, as a thing impoſſible or incredible in Nature, and unconceivable by the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding: And herein they are the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Sadduces, who denied <hi>Angels and Spirits,</hi> and thereby the immortality of the Soul, <hi>and the Reſurrection of the dead;</hi> which great Articles of Faith are call'd in queſtion, and the Objections againſt them greedily receiv'd and vented by the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Atheiſts of our Age, who take the Notion of a Spirit for a vain chimerical thing, that hath no exiſtence but in the deluded Fancies of ſome melancholy and miſtaken Perſons.</p>
            <p>Now this disbelief of Spirits is only to make way for the denial of a God, who
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:106946:40"/> being of a Spiritual and immaterial Nature muſt be ſet aſide together with them. And hence they would perſwade the World, that Men in believing a Deity, are only haunted with an imaginary Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parition, and merely ſcar'd with the Dreams and Phantaſms of their own Brain.</p>
            <p>But why may not ſome Beings be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd to exiſt without Matter, as well as others with it? is Matter, which is but the droſſy part and dregs of the Univerſe, ſo neceſſary and eſſential to Being, that 'tis not poſſible for any to be without it? where lies the contradiction of an imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial Subſtance, that it ſhould be ſo hard to be conceiv'd? nay, does not the Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Perfection of ſome Beings require us to abſtract from Matter in our concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of them? and to aſcribe the Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of their Operations to a Principle real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſtinct from it? Is not Matter of it ſelf an unactive, dull, and ſluggiſh thing, void of all ſenſe and underſtanding? and does it not require a more refined Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance to give it Motion and activity? What is the Body but a dead, heavy, and lumpiſh Carcaſs, without a Soul to actuate and enliven it? neither would the Angels be the nimble and ſwift-wing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Meſſengers of Heaven, if they were
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:106946:41"/> clogg'd with Matter, to check and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tard their Motion. If we Mount up in our Contemplations to the Supreme Being and maker of all things, we muſt conceive of him as an Eternal, Independant and Spiritual Subſtance, void of all Corporei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Matter, and ſubſiſting of himſelf, by the abſolute fulneſs of his own Nature; for the Notion of a God implies a Being that hath all poſſible Perfections, and therefore we are ſo to conceive of him, as to abſtract and remove from all manner of defect and imperfection: Now materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality is a great defect in the Being to which it belongs; for beſide that 'tis a clog to its activity, it confines and limits it to one place, and ſo is oppoſite to the Immenſity, Omnipreſence and Omniſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of a Deity, who as it made Heaven and Earth by his Power, ſo muſt be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to fill both with his Preſence.</p>
            <p>Again, Matter makes a thing to be Diviſible, and conſequently liable to Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, which is utterly inconſiſtent with the Eternity, and other Perfections of the Divine Nature: So that Reaſon wills us to abſtract from the imperfections of Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in our apprehenſions of a God, and to conceive of him as a Spiritual and imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial Subſtance.</p>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:106946:41"/>
            <p>But how comes the Atheiſt to take this for an irrational or unintelligible Notion? Why, he tells us that all the knowledge we have of things, comes from our Senſes; and ſince we cannot ſee or feel a Spirit, nor arrive to the knowledge of it by any of our Senſes, we can form no Idea of ſuch a thing.</p>
            <p>But is nothing to be believ'd, but what we have ſome information of from our Senſes? How then ſhall we believe we have a Soul, of which none of our Senſes can give us any information? for if it be at all, it muſt be a Spiritual and immate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Subſtance, which cannot incur into or be diſcern'd by any of them: Beſide, are there not many noble Effects and Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations that proceed from an inviſible Cauſe? Do we not find, that we can reaſon, judge, and inferr one thing from another, tho' we ſee not the Principle from whence they come? Have we not an Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Will, and Affections, to know, chuſe, and affect things, tho' the Spring of them occur not to any of our Senſes? Do we not find a World made and preſerv'd, tho' we ſee not that inviſible hand that firſt did the one, and ſtill continues the other?</p>
            <p>Indeed, had we no higher Principle of knowledge in us, than our Senſes, it would be hard to form a Notion of God,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:106946:42"/> or any Spiritual and immaterial Subſtance, becauſe theſe things cannot be the Object of Senſation; but having a ſuperior Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, that is a Mind within us, that can raiſe us above all groſs and Corporeal Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; 'tis eaſie to conceive that a Spiritual Subſtance may be diſcern'd by the Mind, tho' it cannot be the Object of our Senſes: Are there not many Truths in all Arts and Sciences, that fall not under the Cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance of any of our Senſes? Yea, are not the Eſſences of all things inviſible, and diſcoverable only by the Powers and Saga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of the Mind, which from the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Effects, can judge of the inward Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Cauſes? The Underſtanding can penetrate much farther into the inſide of things, than our Senſes or Fancy can en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able us to do; we find the Mind can and frequently does correct the Errors of Senſe and Imagination, of which many inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces might be given, if it were needful to enlarge.</p>
            <p>But this is ſufficient to make it evident, that there is a higher Principle of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge within us, than that of our outward Senſes; and that many things are know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and intelligible by the one, that are not convey'd by the other: So that 'tis falſe Reaſoning to infer, that the Mind can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not have a Notion or Idea of a Spiritual
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:106946:42"/> and immaterial Subſtance, becauſe it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be the Object of Senſation.</p>
            <p>Again, the Atheiſt tells us, that the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a God ſuppoſes him to be Infinite and Incomprehenſible, and therefore it muſt be altogether unconceiveable by Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Underſtanding, which cannot graſp Infinity, or comprehend what is Incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible.</p>
            <p>But may not the Mind apprehend ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of a Deity, tho' it cannot compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the whole of him? Is it wiſe arguing, becauſe we have not all knowledge, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we have none at all? If we know as much of him, as the greatneſs of the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and the ſlenderneſs of our Faculties will admit; that is, if we know him to be a Being abſolutely and eminently per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, without the leaſt degree of defect or imperfection, is not this ſufficient to create a Notion and Belief of him? There is ſcarce any inferior Being that we can fully comprehend, and becauſe we un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand not all Myſteries in Nature, ſhall we conclude from thence, that we are quite ignorant, and can have no Notion or Idea of any thing? This will lead to downright Scepticiſm, and make us believe we know nothing. Beſide, we may know as much of him, as 'tis fit for us now to know; we are not at preſent able to receive the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:106946:43"/> full knowledge and ſplendor of the Deity, a great part whereof is reſerv'd for the Happineſs of a future State, when <hi>we ſhall ſee God, as he is;</hi> and tho' we here <hi>know but in part, ſhall then know even as we are known;</hi> and therefore 'tis monſtrouſly unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to quarrel with the Notion and Idea of a God, or think it altogether unconceiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, becauſe we cannot comprehend his infinite Perfections, in this preſent imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ſtate, wherein we know but little of any thing elſe.</p>
            <p>But how does the Atheiſt account for all theſe noble Effects and Operations of the Mind, without the Notion of a Spirit? Why, by reſolving all into Matter and Motion: For he tells us, that ſome of the finer and more ſubtle parts of Matter, call'd Atoms, being in continual motion, lucki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fall into thoſe configurations, by which all this is perform'd without the help or direction of a Deity: And that ſome hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to be wiſer and more knowing than others, proceeds from ſome of thoſe more refined parts of Matter falling accidental<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into more happy forms and contextures in them, than they do in others, and ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of believing in God, they believe only in Matter and Motion. A great piece of <hi>Subtilty indeed!</hi> to ſublimate Matter into Spirit, and to aſcribe the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:106946:43"/> Acts and Operations in the World, to the moſt unactive and ſluggiſh of all things in it. But whence ſhould Matter have this Motion, which neither is nor hath in it any ſelf-moving Principle? Why, of this no account can be given without ſome Spiritual Being, that muſt give it all its activity. Can dull Matter of it ſelf infer one thing from another, and perform thoſe reflex Acts, which we find in rational Beings? Can it range the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſe in Thought and Contemplation? Or dive into profound Speculations? No, theſe things require another and higher Principle, than ſtupid and ſenſeleſs Matter, and owe their riſe to ſome more refin'd, ſpiritual, and intelligent Being.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, The Notion of a Spirit is ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to the ſolving of theſe and a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand other difficulties, that none but ſuch as are wholly immers'd in Matter can doubt or disbelieve it. I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>
                  <hi>SIR,</hi> 
               </salute>
               <signed>Yours, A. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="letter">
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:106946:44"/>
            <head>LETTER X.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>ANother Device of the Atheiſt, is his taking occaſion from the unequal diſtribution of Earthly Things, to queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on both the Being and Providence of a God: They ſee Good Men afflicted, and the Wicked in great proſperity; which they think could not be, if the World were govern'd by ſo Wiſe, Juſt, and Excellent a Being as is pretended.</p>
            <p>This is a Quarrel of an ancient date, or an old ſtumbling Block, that hath trip'd up the Heels of many: We read of it in <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>'s days, who was himſelf in great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of ſtumbling at it; for himſelf tells us, that <hi>his Feet were almoſt gone, and his Steps had well nigh ſlipt, when he ſaw the Wicked in great proſperity; that they were not in trouble like other folk, not plagued like other Men; but were luſty and ſtrong, their Eyes ſtanding out with Fatneſs, having as much as heart could wiſh;</hi> whilſt better men than they look'd meager and thin, being pinch'd with want, and <hi>chaſtened every morning:</hi> This made him begin to doubt,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:106946:44"/> whether there were any wiſe and Supreme Being that order'd theſe things: <hi>I beheld</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly flouriſhing like a green Bay-tree,</hi> and the Righteous Man at the ſame time drooping and hanging the head like a whither'd leaf; <hi>verily I have cleans'd my heart in vain, and waſhed mine hands in innocency:</hi> Meaning, that he had taken pains to be Religious to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, when others that neglected it, far'd much better than he.</p>
            <p>Again, we find theſe things objected in the days of <hi>Plutarch, Seneca,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Heathen Moraliſts, who by the bare help of Natural Light, went a great way to the ſolving of this Riddle of Divine Providence: Tho' many of the Poets con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded the World to be govern'd by blind Chance and Fortune, from the promiſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous event and diſtribution of theſe things: And there are but too many ſtill, who obſerving the Miſeries of Good Men, and the Proſperities of bad, are led to arraign the Juſtice of Providence, and from thence to deny the very Being of a God.</p>
            <p>But is this any tolerable Plea for Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſm? No, in no wiſe; for ſome of the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer and ſoberer Heathens have diſcover'd ſuch weighty Reaſons for this kind of deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the Sons of Men, as are abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly ſufficient to vindicate the Juſtice of
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:106946:45"/> Divine Providence; God's forbearing the Wicked, may be to propound the Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of his Goodneſs and Patience, to give them time for Amendment, to leave them without excuſe, and to make their Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the more terrible and remarkable at laſt. Beſide,</p>
            <p>Their Proſperity is not ſo great as we vainly imagine, for 'tis oft-times embitter'd with the ſting of an evil Conſcience, and attended with fearful Expectations of Wrath, and the Terrors of an approaching Judgment.</p>
            <p>Neither are the Sufferings of the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous founded on leſs weighty Cauſes; for theſe are no other than the Diſcipline and Corrections of a Heavenly Father, for their future good: They are deſign'd merely for the exerciſes of patience, and the tryals of their Faith and Conſtancy, which if manfully born, will tend to the encreaſe of their Reward, and add a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter weight and luſtre to their Crown of Glory.</p>
            <p>Theſe with many other Conſiderations of great Moment, ſufficient to ſolve this difficulty, you may find inſiſted on at large by <hi>Plutarch, Epictetus, Simplicius, Seneca,</hi> and others, to whom I refer you; all which being the plain diſcoveries of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Reaſon, render this Objection ſo far
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:106946:45"/> from any juſt Plea for Atheiſm, that 'tis a plain proof of the contrary, and may make all Men ſay, <hi>verily there is a God, that judgeth the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But how then come Men to be ſo miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by this means, or where lies the miſtake in this matter? Why, this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds partly from a fond and immoderate eſtimation of worldly Proſperity; and partly, likewiſe,</p>
            <p>From ſome wrong Notions, that are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain'd about the Afflictions and Miſeries of this preſent Life. For when Men ſo overvalue the good things of this World, as to think it impoſſible for any to be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py without them; and ſo miſtake the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils and Adverſities of it, as to judge all Men miſerable and unhappy that fall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them; 'tis no wonder, if they accuſe the diſpenſations of Providence, and quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel with the manager and diſpoſer of them: He that takes Wealth and Honour to be the ſole Rewards of Virtue, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently to be the proper Lot and Portion of Righteous Men, may be eaſily induc'd to complain of the hard fare of good Men, that want them; and he that hath ſuch terrible apprehenſions of Adverſity, as to look upon it as the puniſhment and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of Unrighteouſneſs, may envy and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaud the good Fortune of bad Men, who
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:106946:46"/> ſo often eſcape them. Now both theſe are groſs miſtakes, and have unhappily led ſome Men into Atheiſm.</p>
            <p>To Rectifie which, you muſt know, that Affliction is ſomtimes a greater Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing than Proſperity; the one ſerving to make Men better, the other worſe. There be few that, in <hi>Pindar</hi>'s Phraſe, can <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, rightly manage great Proſperity: Yea, too many are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done by it to Eternity, and make that, which was deſign'd for their good, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Inſtrument of their ruin. But</p>
            <p>Where lies the danger of Proſperity? Why,</p>
            <p>Firſt, It tempts many unto Pride, and makes them too apt to forget both God and themſelves; <hi>Jeſurun waxed Fat and kicked,</hi> his Abundance made him bold and inſolent, and lifted up both his Heart and his Heel too againſt his Maker: <hi>David</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd of the wicked that proſper'd in his days, that <hi>Pride compaſſed them about as a chain, and violence cover'd them as a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> And this made them <hi>ſpeak of wicked Blaſphemies, and ſet their talk againſt the moſt high,</hi> Pſal. 73. 8, 9. Yea, he himſelf felt ſomething of this Tumour, for he ſaid in his Proſperity, that he <hi>ſhould never be moved:</hi> he began to caſt off all dependance upon God, and to rely only on his own
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:106946:46"/> ſtrength: And therefore we find <hi>Agar</hi> praying againſt Riches, leſt <hi>being full, he ſhould deny God, and ſay, who is the Lord?</hi> Prov. 30. 8, 9.</p>
            <p>Again, Proſperity tempts many unto Wantonneſs and Luxury; Men's corrupt Natures too often turning the Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to Virtue, into the incentives to Vice, and making their Plenty the fewel of their Luſt and Vanity. By which means, their Riches ſerve only to inflame their reckoning, and their abuſed Gifts and Talents do but ſink them the deeper into Eternal Miſery: The ſenſe of this rectifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Pſalmiſt's miſtake in this matter, and kept him from grieving or grudging at the ſhort-liv'd Proſperity of the Wicked; for when <hi>he went into the Sanctuary, he ſoon <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtood the end of thoſe Men; how they were ſate in ſlippery places, from whence they were ſuddenly caſt down, and came to a fearful end;</hi> from whence he learn't ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to pity, than envy that Proſperity, which had ſo fatal an iſſue, and ſerv'd merely to fatten them for the ſlaughter. As you may Read at large in the 73 Pſalm.</p>
            <p>But is Adverſity the cure of theſe Evils; and do Afflictions beſt tend to prevent the danger of them? Yes; for theſe help to keep Men humble, ſenſible of their weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:106946:47"/> and dependance upon a ſuperior Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and make them look up to him, from whom both Trouble and Deliverance come: Indeed Afflictions naturally lead Men to conſider; he that feels the ſmart of the Rod, will naturally look to him that ſtrikes, and conſider too the Reaſon of his inflicting it; and ſince Afflictions ſpring not out of the Duſt, they direct our Contemplations higher, and ſhew us the Divine Hand that ſends them, by which means we are brought to <hi>hear the voice of the Rod, and of him that appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it: In their Afflictions</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>they will ſeek me early;</hi> the Mariners <hi>in a Storm call each upon their God,</hi> whoſe Being and Providence in a Calm they had utterly forgotten: <hi>Before I was afflicted</hi> (ſaith the Pſalmiſt) <hi>I went aſtray, but now I have learn't thy Statutes; and therefore thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully acknowledg'd, that God of very faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs had cauſed him to be troubled:</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity and trouble have reduc'd many, that were miſs-led and corrupted by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity: Riches (ſaith the Philoſopher) are not to be reputed good things, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the worſt as well as the beſt have them; neither are Afflictions to be reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd evil things, therefore the beſt as well as the worſt undergo them.</p>
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:106946:47"/>
            <p>Theſe things are not only agreeable to, but diſcoverable likewiſe by the Light of Reaſon, to which if we add the greater Light of Revelation in this matter, you will ſee greater cauſe to dread, than de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire Proſperity, and that we ſhould be ſo far from being afraid, or aſham'd, that we ought rather to <hi>glory in Tribulations.</hi> In a Word,</p>
            <p>If we rightly conſider the many and great dangers of Proſperity, and compare them with the many and vaſt advantages of Affliction, we may ſoon ſee this ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling-block of the Atheiſt to vaniſh, and that the Proſperity of bad, and Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of good Men, are ſo far from an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument againſt the Being and Providence of God, that they are a very ſtrong Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Confirmation of Both. I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>
                  <hi>SIR,</hi> 
               </salute>
               <signed>Yours, A. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="letter">
            <pb n="86" facs="tcp:106946:48"/>
            <head>LETTER XI.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAving in my laſt remov'd that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient ſtumbling-block of Atheiſm, taken from the Adverſities of Good, and the Proſperity of bad Men. I proceed now to a later</p>
            <p>Device of the Atheiſt, which is, his taking advantage from the many Sects and Differences in Religion, to lay aſide all; and from Mens Diſagreement about the way and manner of worſhipping God, to ſettle in a total neglect and contempt of him: This is too obvious in experience, to need any proof; for may we not day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee the ſenſe of Religion to wear off from the Minds of Men, by the ſtir that is made about it? Are not the impreſſions of Virtue and Goodneſs mightily defac'd by our Diviſions? So that it cannot be doubted, but the different Sects and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions of our Age are a great Cauſe of that Atheiſm and Irreligion that ſo much abound in it: 'Tis too well known, that
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:106946:48"/> ſome Perſons who have been well enough affected to Religion, and had no ſmall zeal for, and ſatisfaction in it, have yet by falling into the ways of Separation contracted that giddineſs and inſtability, as to loſe all; and by running from one Sect to another, have run themſelves out of breath, and made their laſt reſort into Atheiſm; and others perceiving their claſhing and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtancy, have gone the ſame way, and thrown up all.</p>
            <p>But what influence have Differences and Diviſions in Religion upon the producing of Atheiſm? Why great, ſundry ways: As, Firſt, Diviſions tend to expoſe Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and render it vile and deſpicable; for when Men behold it to ſet one another by the Ears, and to engage them in end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs quarrels and diſputes, they come to deſpiſe and think meanly of it; and ſo are eaſily induc'd to abandon that which breeds ſo much diſcord and animoſity: They are apt to think, that Religion (if there were any ſuch thing) would be a more peaceable, quiet, and harmleſs thing, and have other Effects upon the Minds of Men; but finding it to create little elſe than fewds and differences among the Profeſſors of it, they come to entertain low and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible thoughts of it; and being made only a Bone of Contention, think it good
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:106946:49"/> for nothing but to be thrown away. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly.</hi> Diviſions beget thoſe doubts and uncertainties about Religion, that unſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Mens minds, and bring them into ſuch a Maze, that they know not where to fix: And in this tumult and confuſion of thoughts, many are tempted to throw up all, rather than wander about in ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainties, and loſe themſelves in a crowd of endleſs and diſputable Opinions. Moreover,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>3dly.</hi> Among the numerous Sects and Parties that are in Religion, there can be but one in the Right; for tho' error be In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite, yet Truth is but one; and where to find this among a numberleſs Sett of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders, is they think a matter of ſo much labour and difficulty, that they chuſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to let all alone, than to be at the pains and trouble of ſuch an Enquiry. Beſide,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>4thly.</hi> Some perſons having diſcover'd the folly and falſhood of ſome darling O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions they formerly admir'd, are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by induc'd to ſuſpect all the reſt: And o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers having found out the Cheat and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſture of many more, are apt to conclude the reſt to be no better: All which have an eaſie and natural tendency towards A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſm,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:106946:49"/> and are made uſe of by many to that end.</p>
            <p>Yea all that are indifferent in matters of Religion, and, with <hi>Gallio,</hi> care for none of theſe things (of which the World affords but too many) all ſuch I ſay will be glad to have ſo plauſible a pretence and excuſe for their Irreligion; and they whoſe intereſt and deſign it is to have no Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, will be ſure to lay hold of this and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther advantages againſt it. In a word, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions naturally deſtroy that Love and Charity which is the <hi>Bond of perfectneſs,</hi> and the life of all true Religion, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe neceſſarily beget that Hatred, Strife, and Animoſity, that is the ground-work of Atheiſm, Confuſion, and every Evil work.</p>
            <p>Now here it may not be amiſs to ſtay a while, and conſider the great Evil and Danger of our unhappy Diſſentions; what unſpeakable miſchief they do in the World, and particularly what an apparent handle they give to Atheiſm, being too great an occaſion for it, and putting too fair a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour upon it. For by raiſing theſe diſputes, they do but raiſe a miſt before the Eyes of the People, whereby many are wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tided and led into Atheiſm, and harden'd in their disbelief and contempt of all Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; and there fore 'twas a wiſe and whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:106946:50"/> piece of Advice of the Apoſtle, to <hi>mark thoſe that cauſe Diviſions and avoid them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither will it be amiſs, if the Authors and Abetters of theſe Diviſions will ſet down and conſider, what account they will be able to give, for thoſe many and great Evils, that apparently proceed from them: For if we are forbidden to lay any ſtumbling-Block or occaſion of falling in our Brother's way, how will theſe Men an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for all that Irreligion that hath been evidently occaſioned by this means? Or what Plea will they make for all that Schiſm and Atheiſm, into which ſo many are hereby betray'd? This is a Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of greater Moment than ſome are aware of; for tho' offences may <hi>and will come, yet woe be to them by whom the offence cometh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But are theſe Differences and Diviſions in Religion a ſufficient pretence and excuſe for Atheiſm? No, far from it; for tho' ſuch are accountable to God, that give the occaſion; yet that will not juſtifie or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe thoſe that take it; this being an Evil which they are ſufficiently forewarn'd of, and therefore ſhould be forearm'd againſt it: So that all the Atheiſm occaſion'd from hence, proceeds rather from an Obſtinacy and Perverſeneſs in the Will, than from
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:106946:50"/> any defect of Light or Knowledge in the Underſtanding.</p>
            <p>And here we find the Atheiſts, who would be thought Men of the deepeſt reach and inſight into theſe things, guilty of very foul and falſe Reaſoning in this matter: For,</p>
            <p>Firſt, What tho' ſome Opinions in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion have been found to be falſe, will it follow thence, that there is none true? There are ſome that have entertained wrong Notions in all Arts and Sciences, yea have maintain'd falſe Problems even in the Mathematicks themſelves; and will any conclude from thence, that they are all lies and falſities? This Principle would deſtroy all knowledge, and lead Men to deny and disbelieve every thing: There have been no doubt Hereticks and Schiſmaticks in all Ages, who have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpous'd many Errors and miſtaken Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons about the Worſhip of God; and will any infer from thence, that all Religion is impoſture? Certainly this is very bad arguing, and will lead Men to the heighth of Scepticiſm and Infidelity. Again,</p>
            <p>What tho' Men differ about ſome things, will it follow thence that they agree in nothing? And if (as one hath well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd) their diſagreement be an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the falſhood of ſome things; why
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:106946:51"/> is not their Agreement as good an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the truth of other? The diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences in Religion are commonly about the Circumſtances of it, as about the Modes of Worſhip and Diſcipline; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as Men generally agree in the Matters of Faith and Eſſentials of Religion; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed there is nothing wherein all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind do more univerſally agree, than in the Belief and Worſhip of a God: And is it not unreaſonable, becauſe they may dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer in ſome things, to ſuſpect the Truth of that wherein they are all agreed? He that finds himſelf inclin'd to make this bad uſe of Mens diſputes, and to improve theſe petty differences into Atheiſm, may do well to ſit down and conſider how far Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is concern'd in them, which if he can be perſwaded to do, he will ſoon ſee that theſe things do not affect the Truth and Foundation of it, in which they are all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed, but only the beauty and ornament of the Superſtucture, they refer rather to matters of Speculation than Practice: And if any have various Sentiments about the Ornaments and Out-works of a Building, ſure that can be no Reaſon either to diſtruſt or ſubvert the Foundation. I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>
                  <hi>SIR,</hi> 
               </salute>
               <signed>Yours, A. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="letter">
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:106946:51"/>
            <head>LETTER XII.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Shew'd in my laſt, the perverſe uſe which the Atheiſt makes of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputes and Differences that are found in the World about matters of Religion: I proceed in this to Another Device much like it; which is, his taking occaſion from the Hypocriſie and bad lives of ſome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders to it, to conclude all Religion to be falſe, and from thence to fall into Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſm and Infidelity.</p>
            <p>This is a frequent and fatal practice, of which our Age does afford many ſad and doleful inſtances: there are ſome who will be at no pains to examine the truth or falſhood of any Religion, but take it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on truſt, as the Cuſtom of the Country where they live, or as 'tis deriv'd down to them by their Parents or Anceſtors: Now theſe lie open to all the aſſaults of Atheiſm, and being altogether unguarded againſt them, are but too ready to ſurrender upon any ſummons, and to yield to every temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to it: Their Faith, for lack of being Catechiz'd and well-principl'd in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:106946:52"/> hath no firm bottom, but lies wholly in the power of a corrupt and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant Will, which will move as intereſt and inclination lead it, ſo that as ſoon as they become wicked enough, to need A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſm for a Refuge, they will be ready to flie to it: And therefore we are bid to try and examine the Truth of Doctrines, and be ready to give a Reaſon of the Faith and Hope that is in us, when ever we are ask'd or call'd to it, that being well-ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Truth of Religion, we may ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to it againſt all oppoſition, and ſtand the ſhock of the fierceſt Temptations. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain,</p>
            <p>There are others, who think ſometimes upon Religion, and make ſome enquiry into it, but yet judge of the truth or falſhood of it, not by the ſoundneſs of its Precepts, but by the Lives and Practices of thoſe that make the greateſt profeſſion of it: Theſe likewiſe to ſave the trouble of a deep and impartial ſearch into the grounds and principles upon which Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion ſtands, enquire what others think of it, who by their pretences ſeem beſt to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it; and becauſe Mens Actions are the beſt diſcovery of their thoughts and opinions of things; they judge of what they think in theſe matters, by what they ſee them do; ſo that when they ſee ſuch
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:106946:52"/> Mens Practices give the Lye to their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and find them act as as if they did not believe what they ſay, this makes them think that there is no Reaſon to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it, and that Religion is nothing elſe but a cunning Device, made uſe of by ſome Men to carry on their worldly Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and Deſigns. This no doubt hath drawn many into Atheiſm, and harden'd others in it. The many vile tricks that have been play'd under the Mask of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, the gilding of Treaſon and Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion with a ſpecious pretence of Zeal for God's Glory, and hiding Faction and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition under the colours of Reformation, have made many ſuſpect the whole for a Contrivance, and to caſt it off as a Syſtem of Lies and Impoſtures.</p>
            <p>But is it a true and ſafe Rule, to judge of the truth of Religion by the lives of thoſe that profeſs it? No, a very unſafe and crooked one: For,</p>
            <p>Though the Hypocrite that plays this game, ſhall dearly rue hereafter for all the Evil done by this means; tho' his por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of miſery and damnation will be hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vier and hotter than others, for laying ſuch a ſtumbling block in their way, by which ſo many fall to their Eternal Ruin; yet this will not excuſe the folly of ſuch as ſuffer themſelvs to be miſs-led and betra'y'd
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:106946:53"/> by it, nor juſtifie ſuch Atheiſtical Concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons drawn from it: Example you know is a falſe and fallacious Rule to walk by; for ſince the generality of Men leave the way in which they ſhould walk, to follow them, or infer our Duty from them, is for the moſt to go aſtray.</p>
            <p>But they draw this Concluſion (they ſay) not from the looſe and debauch'd part of the World, that have no ſenſe of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but from the ſtricter ſort, that make the higheſt pretenſions to it, and ſeem to have the deepeſt impreſſions of it; and if theſe make it evident by their lives, that they believe little or nothing of it, what can we think of it, but as a mere Deluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? But do not Men act ſometimes againſt their own perſuaſion? And are not too many carried away by the ſway of their Luſts and corrupt Deſigns, againſt the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victions of their own Mind? That Men ſometimes knowingly and wilfully com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit great ſins, and cover vile enormities under a cloak of greater ſanctity, is a matter indeed to be lamented, but cannot reaſonably be urg'd as an Argument a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Religion: Will any think that a Cheat, becauſe ſome that do ill things are found to be ſo? And if theſe act ſo bad a part, ſhall any be encourag'd by it to act a worſe? Sure this is very bad arguing, and ſuch
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:106946:53"/> as cannot well be own'd by any, that would be thought Men of Senſe and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            <p>'Tis not unuſual for Mens words to be better than their Actions; and in ſuch caſes the wiſeſt courſe is to do as they ſay, and not as they do. This direction we find given with Relation to the Phariſees, who ſate in <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Chair, and ſpake many good things from it, tho' their doings ran counter to their Doctrines; <hi>what</hi> therefore <hi>they ſay,</hi> we <hi>are bid to do, but not to do after their works, for they ſay and do not.</hi> Certainly, 'tis a much better courſe to learn from others bad lives to amend our own, than to take occaſion from thence to grow worſe, and to caſt off all fear of God from before our Eyes.</p>
            <p>Beſide, have not ſome Men bad deſigns to carry on? And do they ſtick at any ways or means to promote them? May not the beſt things be abus'd to evil purpoſes? And is nothing true or good, becauſe it may be made to ſerve bad ends?</p>
            <p>Now tho' theſe falſe tricks of Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, may be a good Reaſon why we ſhould not believe every Spirit, or be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away by vain pretences; yet they can be no Argument againſt the Truth of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, no more than it would be to affirm, that there are no true Diamonds, becauſe
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:106946:54"/> there are ſo many counterfeits. How then comes it to paſs, that ſo many are caught in this ſnare, and miſ-led by ſuch an appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent fallacy? Why, this muſt proceed partly</p>
            <p>From ſome Mens averſneſs to Religion, heighten'd by a ſtrong deſire to follow the ſwinge of their corrupt inclinations, and to be freed from any check or reſtraint it might lay upon them. And,</p>
            <p>Partly likewiſe, from their too great proneneſs to Atheiſm, which makes them lay hold on any thing, tho' never ſo mean, that may give any countenance or encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to it.</p>
            <p>In ſhort then, The Atheiſts great apt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to draw ſuch bad Concluſions from Lives may be a good Caution againſt all Immorality and Vice, by which the name of God is Blaſphem'd; but can by no means be made a Plea for Atheiſm, or give any juſt Cauſe to diſcard Religion as an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſture. I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>
                  <hi>SIR,</hi> 
               </salute>
               <signed>Yours, A. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="letter">
            <pb n="99" facs="tcp:106946:54"/>
            <head>LETTER XIII.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAving in the foregoing Letters ſhew'd the weakneſs of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts Arguments againſt a Deity: I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in this to another Artifice he makes uſe of to undermine the Belief and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of him; and that is to Scoff at and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ride Religion, and if he cannot Argue it, to endeavour to Laugh it out of the World. This is done by thoſe, who would be thought to be the knowing Men and Wits of the Age; who firſt try the ſtrength of their Reaſon, and when that fails, fly to Art to ſupport their Atheiſm, and ſet their Wits at work to Rally and Ridicule Religion.</p>
            <p>This is a degree of wickedneſs, which Men are not wont to arrive to preſently, for the Pſalmiſt intimates, that they muſt <hi>walk a while in the Counſel of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly, and ſtand in the way of Sinners, before they can ſet down and ſettle in the Chair of the Scorner.</hi> Pſal. 1. 1. When they are ſeated there, and accuſtomed themſelves to this vile practice, they ſoon loſe the ſenſe of a Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and ſo perſwade themſelves and others
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:106946:55"/> that there is no God, becauſe they have the impudence to ſcorn and deſpiſe him.</p>
            <p>But do theſe Men think by Laughter to alter the Nature of Good and Evil? Or that a God of Infinite Power, Wiſdom and Juſtice, will be thus play'd or droll'd out of his Being? Can they hope to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail by leveling their Blaſphemies againſt the moſt High; <hi>ſetting their Mouth againſt the Heavens, and cauſing their Tongue to walk through the Earth?</hi> No, certainly; this is both a fruitleſs and frivolous attempt, for <hi>he that ſitteth in the Heavens will laugh them to ſcorn, the Lord ſhall have them in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What end then can theſe Men propoſe in ſuch a vile piece of Wickedneſs? Why, this is done,</p>
            <p>Firſt, to gain to themſelves the Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of being Wits; which they endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to do, by expoſing the moſt ſerious things: The life and picquancy of Wit, (as one hath well obſerv'd) lies in the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizingneſs of its conceits and expreſſions; and conſequently to Ridicule things Sacred, which ought in Reaſon to be Priviledg'd from it, is moſt apt to aſtoniſh and ſurprize the hearers; and if any (as light and vain Perſons are wont to be) are thereby moved to Laughter, they are tickled with the
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:106946:55"/> conceit, and thereby pleaſe and inure themſelves to this impious practice.</p>
            <p>This way the dulleſt perſons (if they will be Prophane enough) may be eaſily dubb'd Wits, by venturing to ſay thoſe rude things of God and Religion, which no wiſe Man would preſume to utter, and this proves a ſtrong temptation to many who have no other way to be thought witty. Again,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly.</hi> This is thought by ſome a genteel and brave thing, to go out of the common Road, and to caſt off thoſe fears which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are aw'd and terrifi'd withal; they reckon it a ſort of Gallantry of Spirit, to be above the frights that poſſeſs Vulgar Minds, and to ſhake off thoſe Fetters of Religion, with which the generality ſuffer themſelves tamely to be bound; and the better to break theſe Chains, they labour to break their Jeſts upon them. Moreover,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>3dly.</hi> This is done to give the better countenance to their ſinful practices and immoralities; for if they can expoſe Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and make Religion ridiculous, they may act their Vices with the greater grace, and follow the ſway of their Luſts with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſhame or controul. Beſide, they think it a good Plea for their Wickedneſs, that they do not therein contradict any Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple they profeſs, they act ſuitably to what
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:106946:56"/> they pretend, and therefore to put the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Face upon their Vices, they laugh at thoſe for Fools, who do not believe and act as they do: Thus by accuſtoming themſelves to ridicule the moſt ſerious things, they bring on a Contempt of God and Religion, and droll themſelves into Atheiſm. But is there any Wiſdom or Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in ſo doing? No, quite otherwiſe; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be more ſottiſh or dangerous; for all ſuch Mirth is no better than Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and this kind of Laughter will ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly end in <hi>weeping, and wailing, and gnaſhing of teeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have heard of ſome, that would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther loſe their Friend than their Jeſt; but 'tis ſtrange that this drolling humour ſhould carry any ſo far, as to make them venture the loſs of the favour of God, the beſt Friend and Benefactor in the World, for the ſake of an idle prophane Jeſt, which taints the Air that gives it breath, and ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther grates upon, or corrupts the Ears of thoſe that hear it.</p>
            <p>But becauſe this is become a too frequent and faſhionable practice, and hath betray'd many into Atheiſm; 'twill be requiſite to lay open the folly and danger of it. And, Firſt, if there were nothing elſe, the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardonable rudeneſs and indecence of this practice, is ſufficient to ſhew it highly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becoming
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:106946:56"/> any perſon of Senſe or Breeding; for ſince Mankind generally profeſs a high eſteem and veneration for God and Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it muſt be a manifeſt breach of Civili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and good Manners to ſcoff at and deride them: The Laws of Converſation require to treat all Men with due reſpect; there is none can hear with patience his Father or his Friend expos'd to Scorn and Deriſion; and what an unparallel'd affront muſt it be to Mankind, to make God and Religion (the deareſt things to them in the world) the ſubject of Contempt and Raillery?</p>
            <p>Again, <hi>2dly.</hi> The mighty influence which the belief of a God hath upon the publick welfare, may convince any conſidering Man of the great Evil of deriding it; he that deſpiſes Religion, cuts the Sinews of Government, and diſſolves the firmeſt Bond of Human Society; for when Men have laugh'd away the Fear of God and the Senſe of Religion, all Obligations of Conſcience are gone with it, and nothing remains to keep them to their duty, but the fear of Men, which is a looſe Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that will vary or ceaſe, as opportunity, intereſt, or humour lead it. Moreover,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>3dly.</hi> To jeſt at, and expoſe Religion, is the groſſeſt abuſe of Wit that can be made of it; for it turns one of the chiefeſt Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Virtue, into an Encouragement
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:106946:57"/> of Vice, and makes that which was given to recreate the Mind, and ſweeten Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, to become the Bane and Peſt of both: Wit (as a great Man hath obſerv'd) is a keen Weapon, as apt for bad as good purpoſes, and therefore a wiſe Man ſhould have the keeping of it, to prevent the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief and danger of its ill management.</p>
            <p>There is a good uſe of Wit in many Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; as to adorn Virtue, and recommend it to the beſt Advantage; to expoſe Vice, and render it as it deſerves, Ridiculous; to ſeaſon Converſation, and to eaſe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Mind under the burden of its Cares; and whilſt it keeps within theſe Bounds, 'tis a uſeful and commendable Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; but when it tranſgreſſes theſe Rules, and breaks in upon God and Religion, it loſeth its name, and degenerates into Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and Impiety.</p>
            <p>Yea, ſuch as would be thought Wits, by jeſting upon ſacred and ſerious things, do but betray the greateſt folly; 'twas the fool that ſaid in his Heart, there was no God; and <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, that none but <hi>Fools make a mock of Sin,</hi> or think of <hi>mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God, who neither can nor will be mocked.</hi> In a word, all prophane Wit is the heighth of folly, and tho' it have never ſo much Salt, cannot be ſavoury, but nauſeous and offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive to all wiſe Men.
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:106946:57"/> 
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> The unſpeakable hazard the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſt runs in deriding Religion, is enough to ſhew the danger and folly of this impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous practice: For if the Atheiſt ſhall find at laſt that there is a God, as undoubtedly he will, what will he ſay for thoſe rude ſcoffs and affronts he hath put upon him? What account can he give for all this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent Buffoonry? What horrour and confuſion of Face muſt needs ſeize them, when the Maker and Judge of the World ſhall avenge this inſolence upon them, and vindicate his Honour in their Eternal De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction? This is a matter well worth their ſerious and timely conſideration, that they may repent and return no more to this Folly: Otherwiſe, if they will conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue to laugh on, and ſcoff at Religion, God Almighty will ſhortly take his turn too, and will <hi>laugh at their Calamity, and mock when their Fear cometh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſhort then, this drolling upon Sacred Things is ſo far from giving any juſt encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to Atheiſm, that 'tis an high Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravation of the Impiety; and all ſuch Mirth will end at laſt in the deepeſt Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>
                  <hi>SIR,</hi> 
               </salute>
               <signed>Yours, A. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="letter">
            <pb n="106" facs="tcp:106946:58"/>
            <head>LETTER XIV.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Proceed now to the laſt, tho' none of the leaſt Artifices to ſupport and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance Atheiſm: For when the Atheiſt is beaten out of all the former ſubterfuges, he hath recourſe to another Device, ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted to him by his ſenſual Luſts and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite. And that is,</p>
            <p>To charge Religion with a fooliſh Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; and that ſuch as embrace it, act upon ſlender and inſufficient Motives. To prove which, they tell us,</p>
            <p>That to part with preſent Certainties, for uncertain Futurities, can be no Act of Wiſdom; for in doubtful Caſes the greateſt Evidence ſhould ſway: Now we are ſure (ſay they) of what is preſent, but can never be ſo of what is future; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he charges it with folly, to deny themſelves the preſent Pleaſures, Profits, and Honours of this World, for a few vain Hopes of better things in another, which perhaps may never come to paſs, and of which none could ever yet give them any certain Evidence.
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:106946:58"/> This, tho' own'd indeed by few, is yet the Senſe and Language of moſt mens Lives and Actions; which ſhew them to be fond to exceſse of theſe Earthly enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but to have little or no regard to the weightier Concerns of Heaven and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity, and, with Martha, <hi>to be cumber'd about many things,</hi> with the neglect of the <hi>one thing neceſſary.</hi> The Epicures Song is, <hi>let us eat and drink, for to morrow we die;</hi> the preſent time is ours, and all that we can call ſo; for the time to come, we know not whoſe it may be, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore 'tis wiſdom to enjoy what we are ſure of, and not to defer or ſuſpend our hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs upon any ſuch future uncertainties.</p>
            <p>But <hi>be not deceiv'd</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>Evil Communications corrupt good Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners;</hi> yea ſuch vain communication cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt mens Minds, debauch their Reaſon, and makes them act like Fools, when they would be thought to talk moſt wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. For,</p>
            <p>Firſt, The preſent Enjoyments of this World, (how confidently ſoever we may call them our own) are infinitely vain and uncertain, and when we think to enjoy moſt of them, frequently leave and lurch our expectations: <hi>Riches take to themſelves wings and fly away,</hi> when we think to hold them faſteſt: The Pleaſures and Delights of
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:106946:59"/> the World are all fleeting and momentany, yea they are imbitter'd with a Sting, and mingled with Sorrow: Honour is a puff of wind that is quickly gone, and he that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mires theſe things, ſets his heart upon <hi>that which is not:</hi> So that the Atheiſt is miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken in his Suppoſition, for theſe preſent things are not ſo certain as he takes them. Neither are they ſo much the Happineſs, as the Trouble and Miſery of human life: the wicked Man knows many times that he plays the Fool in gratifying his Luſts, and owns that he ought to do otherwiſe; he feels a regret and trouble upon his mind, and does not ſo much enjoy, as diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet himſelf in indulging of them. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever,</p>
            <p>The Atheiſt here tells us, that the pleaſures of this life affect his Senſes, he feels himſelf in ſome meaſure pleas'd and delighted with them; and why ſhould he abridge himſelf of ſuch ſenſible Delights, for Future Things, of which he hath no taſt, and can have no aſſurance?</p>
            <p>As for the pleaſures of Senſe, they are in the moſt innocent uſe of them vaſtly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded by the pleaſures of Virtue and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; for theſe have a ſweeter Reliſh on the Mind, and leave far more laſting im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of joy and ſatisfaction, than any ſenſual Delights ever did or can do: And if
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:106946:59"/> this pure delight flow at laſt <hi>into fulneſs of joy,</hi> and run into <hi>thoſe Rivers of pleaſure, that are at Gods right hand for evermore,</hi> there is infinite Reaſon why we ſhould abridge our ſelves in theſe ſenſual Enjoyments, for the fruition of a far more glorious and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Felicity.</p>
            <p>But ſtill the uncertainty and want of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence for theſe things ſticks with the Atheiſt, and makes the parting with the one for the other a fooliſh Bargain; for we never ſaw (ſaith he) nor experienc'd theſe things our ſelves, nor ever ſpake with any one that did.</p>
            <p>But what kind of Evidence is it, that he would have of theſe things? I hope he does not expect more than the nature of the thing will bear, for that would be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable, and ſhew him to be both un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing and uncapable of Conviction. Now God being a ſpiritual and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly an inviſible Subſtance, cannot be prov'd by the Evidence of Senſe, for <hi>no man hath ſeen God at any time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither can a future ſtate, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mences not till after this life, be at preſent viſible, or fall under the tryal or experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of any of our Senſes: ſo that this kind of proof cannot in Reaſon be requir'd in this Caſe, neither can the Atheiſt exact it without wounding his own Cauſe; for nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:106946:60"/> can <hi>Epicurus</hi>'s Atoms, nor <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>'s Eternity of the World be prov'd this way.</p>
            <p>What Aſſurance then have we of theſe Truths? Why, we have the proper, that is a Moral Aſſurance, grounded upon the evident and neceſſary deductions of Reaſon, which is ſufficient to beget a confident Perſwaſion of the truth of them, and to remove all doubts and diſtruſt to the contrary.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, we have as great an Aſſurance of theſe Things, as 'tis poſſible for us to have, ſuppoſing that they are true, which is enough to ſatisfie any reaſonable man in the belief of them: Let us ſuppoſe then that there is a God, that is a Being of all poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Perfections; how may we come to know or be aſſured of it? Why, not by the Evidence of Senſe; for being a Spirit, he cannot fall under the Cognizance of any of our Senſes; the only proof we can have of him, muſt be either from ſome ſecret impreſſions of him upon our Mind, or from ſome viſible Effects and Operations, that can only be aſcrib'd to ſuch a Being; and both theſe we have in this Caſe. Again,</p>
            <p>Suppoſing there be a future ſtate for the Rewarding of Good, and Puniſhing of Bad Men, what proof can we have of it? Why, none from the evidence of Senſe; for things future and at a diſtance are incapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of that kind of proof; all the Aſſurance we can have of it, is from the Attributes
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:106946:60"/> and Perfections of the firſt Cauſe and Maker of all things, whoſe Truth and Faithfulneſs hath declar'd it, and whoſe Mercy and Juſtice neceſſarily require it; for ſince the Obſervation and Violation of his Laws, are not uſually rewarded or Puniſhed in this life, there muſt be ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtate where the honour of thoſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Perfections will be more openly and throughly vindicated.</p>
            <p>The truth is, 'tis not want of Light, but mens ſhutting their Eyes againſt it, that miſs-lead's them in this matter; 'tis a falſe heart that ſuggeſts theſe doubts, and a corrupt Will that pretends lack of ſufficient aſſurance: For Men dayly act upon far leſs Evidence in all other matters, and ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture their Lives and Fortunes upon things that have no higher than this Moral Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty; what wiſe Man ever doubts, whether there be ſuch a place as the <hi>Indies, Spain,</hi> or <hi>Turkey,</hi> tho' perhaps he never ſaw either? Do not many transfer their Eſtates by way of Traffick into Foreign Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, of which they have no other know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, than from the Teſtimony and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of others? And he that ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to believe or act upon this kind of Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty, would be reckon'd no better than a Fool or a Mad-man: And if this ſort of aſſurance be ſufficient to juſtifie our diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:106946:61"/> in the affairs of our Body; why ſhould we diſtruſt it in the matters of our Soul; eſpecially ſince 'tis not poſſible in our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſtate to have any higher?</p>
            <p>But tho' this Evidence (ſaith the Atheiſt) be ſufficient in Temporal Matters; yet a greater Certainty is requiſite in Divine Things, and the weightier Affairs of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. Now tho' this be not wanting to all that are willing to receive it, yet what Reaſon can be given, why that Aſſurance which guides Men in the purſuit of a Leſſer Good, ſhould not influence them much more to obtain a Greater; And that Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence which is ſufficient to prompt them to avoid Temporal Evils, ſhould not more ſtrongly encline them to eſcape thoſe that are Eternal.</p>
            <p>In a Word, The vaſt odds that is on the ſide of Religion, ſhews it to be far from a fooliſh Bargain; for if there be no God or a World to come, the Good Man can be no loſer, for he only parts with his Luſts, which are the ſhame and ſcandal of his Nature, and inſtead of following them, is directed to do what is moſt for his health, intereſt, reputation, and every way moſt conducing to the Peace and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the preſent life: But if there be a God and a future ſtate, as 'tis more than ten thouſand to one there are, he will be
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:106946:61"/> vaſtly a Gainer, for beſide the preſent qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et and ſatisfaction he enjoys here; he is ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur'd of everlaſting Peace and Tranquili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hereafter, and for the poor periſhing trifles of Time; which he now parts with, ſhall be rewarded with the ineffable Joys and Glories of Eternity; and ſure no wiſe Man will charge this with Folly: For if he who hath exchang'd Pebbles for Pearls, is by all thought to have made a wiſe bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, he that parts with the light <hi>Momen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tany things</hi> of this Life, for an <hi>Eternal Crown of Glory</hi> in a better, will in the end be found to have made a much wiſer. I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>
                  <hi>SIR,</hi> 
               </salute>
               <signed>Yours, A. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="letter">
            <head>LETTTER XV.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have in the foregoing Letters; accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to promiſe, ſet forth ſome of the principal Arts and Devices, that are made uſe of to ſupport and countenance Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſm; and likewiſe, according to your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, laid open the Evil and Danger of them.</p>
            <p>But becauſe the Requeſt of your Letter extended not only to the Cauſe, but the Cure of Atheiſm; it will be requiſite; for a Cloſe, to ſubjoyn ſome few Directions to
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:106946:62"/> that end. And here what hath been ſaid touching the Riſe of this Evil, may help us to find out the Remedies of it; for as to know the Cauſe of a Diſtemper, is a fair ſtep towards the Cure, ſo to diſcover the Devices of Atheiſm, is the readieſt way to prevent the Danger, and to be preſerv'd from the Contagion of it.</p>
            <p>But becauſe the Riſe of this Evil is more from the Will and Affections, than from the Mind or Underſtanding, we are to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply our ſelves rather to rectifie the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, than to inform the latter; for Men are not Atheiſts ſo much for want of Knowledge, as for lack of a due Uſe and Application of it. And therefore the</p>
            <p>Firſt and Grand Preſervative againſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſm, muſt be to mortifie and ſubdue all ſinful and ſenſual Luſts, for theſe give the ſtrongeſt byaſs to this Evil, and draw too many into it: We obſerv'd before, that a vicious life makes it Mens intereſt that there be no God, and that makes it their wiſh, and ſoon after their belief that there is none: This is the common and ordinary Road to Atheiſm, and is indeed that <hi>broad way, that leadeth to Deſtruction;</hi> which being ſo eaſie, and ſuitable to Mens vile and vicious Inclinations, many there be that <hi>find and</hi> walk in it.</p>
            <p>But that we may not loſe our ſelves, and
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:106946:62"/> walk on for Company to our own ruin, we are to get out of this broad way, and betake our ſelves into the ſtraighter paths of Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification and Self-denyal, which lying croſs to Mens wicked and corrupt affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, is the true Reaſon that few there be that find it. 'Twas wiſely obſerv'd by a great Man, that the main Reaſon why a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Man becomes an Atheiſt, is becauſe he is a wicked Man, and reſolves to be ſo: Religion would curb them in their Luſts, and therefore they caſt it off, and put all the Scorn they can upon it: So that to cure this Malady, we muſt, in the Prophets Phraſe, <hi>ceaſe to do evil, and learn to do well:</hi> This will take off that wrong byaſs that turns ſo many out of the way, and likewiſe ſet them right in the way that <hi>leads to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> To prevent this growing Evil, let us often meditate upon the admirable Frame and Fabrick of the World, and ſet apart ſome time for the Contemplation of the wonderful Works both of Creation and Providence; theſe will afford ſuch plain Evidence and Demonſtration of a Deity, that 'tis ſcarce poſſible for the moſt profligate Perſon, that will conſider, to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlook them. I have already ſhew'd you the vain Attempts of the Atheiſt, in going about to ſolve the <hi>Phoenomena</hi> of the World without a Supreme Being, either
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:106946:63"/> by affirming that it had no beginning, or that it had its beginning from Chance, or Fortune, both which are attended with ſuch Abſurdities, as are too groſs for any, but an Atheiſts Faith to ſwallow; for which way ſoever we turn our ſelves, we meet with the plain Prints and Footſteps of a Deity.</p>
            <p>If we look upward, the <hi>Heavens declare the glory of God, and the Firmament ſheweth his handy Works;</hi> thoſe glorious Luminaries of Heaven, the Sun, Moon, and Stars, which by their conſtant Influences cheriſh and enlighten the World, mind us of that great Father of Lights, that plac'd them there; the exquiſite Order, Beauty, and ſteady Revolution of thoſe Heavenly Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, which come forth <hi>like a Bridegroom out of their Chambers, and rejoyce as a Giant to run their Courſe,</hi> are ſo many daily and Ocular Demonſtrations of a Supream Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that firſt ſet, and ſtill continues them in motion.</p>
            <p>If we look down upon the Earth, and behold the admirable Frame, Order, and Contrivance of all things in it, we may plainly ſee that of the Apoſtle verified, that God <hi>hath not left himſelf without witneſs;</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Creature bearing their Teſtimony, and directing our Contemplation to him.</p>
            <p>If we take a view of our ſelves, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the curious Needle-work and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>texture
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:106946:63"/> of our Bodies, we may ſee there the Finger of a God; and with the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt break out in admiration of the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Power, Wiſdom, and Goodneſs of our Creator; to which, if we add the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the wonderful Frame and Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Soul, we may ſee the Image and Superſcription of our Maker ſo viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſtampt on it, that any conſidering Man may know whoſe it is, and whence it came.</p>
            <p>If we go lower, to the Creatures ſubject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Man's Dominion, we ſhall find the Birds of the Air ſinging forth the Praiſes of their Maker, the Fiſh of the Sea declare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Wonders of the Deep; and all the Beaſts of the Field, ſo many Heralds and Inſtruments of his Honour. Yea, if we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend to the loweſt rank of Creatures, and behold the Herbs, the Graſs, and the Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Field, we ſhall find Divinity almoſt viſibly Imprinted there; the Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Roſe and the Lilly, which with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any toyl or ſpinning are array'd in that natural gayety and bravery, that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds all the coſtly Attire of <hi>Solomon,</hi> are plain Inſtances of the Wiſdom and Care of a Heavenly Father, who thus <hi>cloaths the graſs of the field,</hi> and provides ſo wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully for all his Creatures.</p>
            <p>Theſe are noble Subjects for our Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; in which we are admirably aſſiſted
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:106946:64"/> by a late Learned Diſcourſe (of Dr. <hi>Pel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi>) concerning the Exiſtence of God, wherein the ingenious Author hath ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently diſplay'd the abſtruſe Myſteries of Nature, and the Wonders both of Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Providence, as is ſufficient for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to ſilence and baffle all the Attempts of Atheiſm: And therefore I ſhall add no more on this pleaſant Subject, but refer you to it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> To prevent this Evil of Atheiſm, let us hearken to the voice of Conſcience ſpeaking within us, and beware of ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling the notices or good motions of it: If we turn our Eyes inward, and conſult our own breaſts, we ſhall find ſomething there that ſecretly tells us when we do well, and when we act amiſs; when we do that which is meet, right, and our bounden Duty, we find a calm and ſereni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty upon our Mind, that chears it with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expreſſible delight and ſatisfaction: When we do what we ought not, we find ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing within that doth reprehend and fly upon us, yea, and gaul us too with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe and anguiſh; inſomuch that there is none, how wicked ſoever, but finds ſometimes a Reluctance in his Spirit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt bad Actions, even when his corrupt Paſſions, Deſigns, and Inclinations draw him moſt ſtrongly to them.</p>
            <p>Now this proceeds from the ſecret calls
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:106946:64"/> and whiſpers of Conſcience, which is a kind of Deputy ſet up in every Man's breaſt, to preſerve the Memory and Fear of a Deity: And therefore, we are to take heed how we deſpiſe the Calls and Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions hereof, for this will lead to a ſear'd Conſcience, and that to Atheiſm.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> To avoid this Evil, we muſt (as much as poſſible) avoid all Atheiſtical Diſcourſe and Company, for theſe are too apt to infuſe bad principles into mens minds, and to inſtil even the poiſon of Atheiſm: Cuſtom you know and Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny have a mighty influence upon Mankind, and always leave either good or bad im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions behind them: if we converſe with wiſe men, <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, we ſhall learn Wiſdom; we ſhall be benefitted by their Diſcourſe and Example, and as one Coal kindles another, ſo we may receive heat and warmth from their Piety and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion: but if we delight in the Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of looſe and vain Perſons, we ſhall learn their practices, and inſenſibly loſe the very Principles of Religion; corrupt Communication naturally tends to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt good manners; frequent ſwearing and curſing take off from the Reverence that is due to the Divine Majeſty, and the lewd Talk and Example of bad com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany gradually wear off all impreſſions of Virtue: Vice is infectious, and communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:106946:65"/> its venom and malignity to ſuch as come near it, and therefore we are to keep at a diſtance from it, and to have <hi>no fellowſhip with the unfruitful works of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but rather reprove them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> To be arm'd againſt Atheiſm, we muſt labour to be well grounded in the Principles of Religion, and not to take up our Faith upon Truſt without Examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. A Tree (you know) that is not well rooted, is liable to be ſhak'd with every wind; and ſuch as are not well-grounded in their Religion, are eaſily toſs'd to and fro, and carried about with every wind of Doctrine: He that for want of inſtruction is unable to give a Reaſon of the Faith that is in him, will be as unable upon any aſſault to give any Reaſon why he ſhould keep it; and ſuch as take up their faith only upon truſt, will be as ready to lay it down again, when a ſtrong temptation calls for it.</p>
            <p>If you obſerve it, 'tis the uncatechiz'd and ill-inſtructed part of Mankind, that fall into irreligion, and are carried captive by infidelity; ſuch as theſe, for want of being well ſeaſon'd in time with pious and ſound Principles, have nothing to hold them; ſo that as they grow up, if their Temper be Sanguine and Jolly, they fall into Lewd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Debauchery; if more ſour and melancholy they fall into Phanaticiſm and Diviſions; and both, tho' going different
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:106946:65"/> ways, meet at laſt in the Center of Atheiſm: Again,</p>
            <p>Mens ſhifting of Principles, for want of ſteadineſs in Religion, and varying from ſound and receiv'd Doctrines, is undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly a great occaſion of Atheiſm; for when Men openly relinquiſh what they have publickly maintain'd, it makes many call in Queſtion the Truth of Religion it ſelf, and to think that all other parts of it have no better grounds than that which they have rejected as groundleſs; and tho' it be unjuſt in any to take this offence, yet 'tis no leſs unſafe for any to give it. Wherefore,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> To prevent this Evil, we muſt beware of being ſeduc'd or drawn into Sects or Parties, for this hath begotten that giddineſs and inſtability, that hath ſhak'd the Faith of many, and unawares led them into Atheiſm.</p>
            <p>Religion hath its Name from binding, and its chief Deſign is to keep Men firm to their Duty to God and Man; now the relaxing of this Bond, lets Men looſe in both, and that brings on Diviſions in point of Worſhip, and Corruptions in point of Manners; both which naturally lead to Irreligion and Atheiſm; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Wiſdom and Piety of a Nation is beſt ſeen in preſcribing good Laws to prevent all looſeneſs and extravagance in both: and as 'tis the Duty of Superiors to
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:106946:66"/> Countenance a well-eſtabliſh'd Religion, by encouraging the Obſervers, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing the Tranſgreſſors of it; ſo is it the unqueſtionable Duty of Subjects to keep cloſe to the Rules of it, without corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing its Doctrine by Hereſie, or breaking its Unity by Schiſms and Diviſions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> To put a ſtop to Atheiſm, we muſt take care to frequent the ſolemn Worſhip of God, and diligently obſerve the ſtated Seaſons of publick and private Devotion; the neglect of this hath been an unhappy occaſion of the growth of this impiety; for the many preſſing Affairs of this World are apt to croud in upon our minds, to engroſs too much of our time and thoughts, and thereby to beget an utter forgetfulneſs of God, and the greater Concerns of another life; to prevent which, God Almighty, to keep up the Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of himſelf for our own good, hath appointed ſome ſolemn Seaſons, in which he hath requir'd us to reſt from all our worldly Cares and Labours, that we may the better attend his Worſhip and Service. Now the obſerving of theſe Seaſons will help to take off our Minds from an inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate purſuit of this World, and fix them on a better, 'twill recollect our ſcatter'd Thoughts, and preſerve a due Senſe of Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety and Religion; the publick Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of thoſe Seaſons ſerve to awaken and
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:106946:66"/> ſtir us up to our Duty, and our Zeal is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed by the concurrence and example of each others Devotion; by which means the Senſe and Fear of God is ſtill kept a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live in our Minds.</p>
            <p>Whereas by a careleſs neglect of Pulick Worſhip, God is in a manner excluded out of all our Thoughts, we become wholly immers'd in the Cares and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of this Life, and ſo naturally ſink into Atheiſm and Impiety. So that to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue ſound and ſerious in Religion, we muſt carefully frequent the Publick Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and be mindful likewiſe of the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of private and ſecret Devotion, for theſe will withdraw our Minds from ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Objects, which are too apt to envei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle us, and lead to the Contemplation of Divine and Heavenly things, by which alone the Senſe of God and Religion can be preſerv'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eighthly,</hi> To this we muſt add the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes of a Holy Life, without which the ſenſe of Religion will inſenſibly wear off and decay: A Profeſſion of Piety without Practice, is like a Tree without Fruit, which commonly dies away, or elſe is cut down and caſt into the Fire; to make a fair ſhew of Religion, without a ſuitable Converſation, is but to deny God with the greater Solemnity, and however ſuch may ſeem to flatter him with their Lips,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:106946:67"/> they Read a Lecture of Atheiſm in their Lives, and cauſe the Name of God to be blaſphem'd. And therefore, that we may not deny God, we muſt <hi>deny all ungodlineſs and worldly luſts, and live righteouſly, ſoberly, and godly,</hi> in this preſent World. Theſe <hi>fruits of righteouſneſs will redound not only to the glory of God,</hi> but to the Credit of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which is beſt kept alive both in our ſelves and in others by this means; <hi>the light of ſuch good works will ſo ſhine before men, as to make them glorifie God in the day of viſitation;</hi> Examples are wont to have a greater force than Precepts; and moſt Men like Sheep are apt to go rather <hi>qua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iter,</hi> than <hi>qua eundum:</hi> And therefore great heed is to be taken to our ways, that we do not by bad Examples draw any from the Truth, or miſ-lead them into the paths of Errour and Wickedneſs: And as this ſhould be obſerv'd by all Men, ſo more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially by ſuch as have any higher Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Church or State, for theſe are like a <hi>City on a Hill,</hi> which lies open to the view of all, their actions are more viſible and exemplary, and leave either a good or bad influence behind them, which ſhould make them the more wary and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, that they give no offence, or be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any an occaſion of falling: By this means we ſhall baniſh Atheiſm, and keep Religion in the World, and thereby at once adorn our Profeſſion here, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:106946:67"/> the Reward annext to it hereafter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> To cure this Evil, let us often ponder upon the extream Folly and Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Atheiſm; the frequent and ſerious Conſideration whereof may help to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie our Minds againſt it, and incline us to hate and abhor ſo vile an Enormity.</p>
            <p>Now the Atheiſt's Folly is ſeen in the badneſs of his arguing, and his Danger in the badneſs of his acting.</p>
            <p>Of the former many inſtances have been given already; to which I ſhall only add one more, to wit, That the Atheiſt, in go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about to prove there is no God, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts to prove a pure Negative, which all wiſe Men know to be not only abſurd, but impoſſible, unleſs where the Being of a thing implies a Contradiction; there in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a Negative may be prov'd, for 'tis good Reaſoning, that a thing is not, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it cannot be; but where the Being of a thing is not impoſſible, as none ever yet pretended the Being of a God to be; there, unleſs our Minds could graſp the Knowledge of all poſſibilities, and compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend all things that are or may be, ſuch Reaſoning muſt be abſurd and inconſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent; for more things have an Exiſtence in Nature, than in our Underſtanding, and many things are and may be which we know not of. Again,</p>
            <p>The Notion of a God implying a Being that hath all poſſible Perfections, to deny
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:106946:68"/> ſuch a Being is (as one hath well obſerv'd) to aſſert a poſſibility impoſſible, which is a flat contradiction. Moreover,</p>
            <p>To deny that God is, is in effect to affirm it impoſſible that he ſhould be; for Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity being an Eſſential and inſeparable Perfection of a Deity, he muſt have been for ever, or elſe he cannot be at all; ſo that if he be not now, he cannot begin to be, it being abſurd to affirm of a Being that hath no beginning, that it may begin to be, which is another of the Atheiſt's Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions, and ſhews him guilty of bad Reaſoning with a witneſs.</p>
            <p>Neither is the Folly of his arguing more apparent, than the Danger of his act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: for he throws himſelf upon the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of all Hazards, upon the greateſt of all Uncertainties, which is a matter never enough to be conſider'd and lamented.</p>
            <p>All that the Atheiſt builds upon, is, that 'tis ſomewhat a doubtful Caſe, whether there be a God or no, and that Men may do well enough without the Belief or Fear of him: But who but a Mad-man would run ſuch a hazard, and ſtake down his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Soul on ſuch a Peradventure? In all doubtful Caſes, a thing may as well be as not be, and therefore matters are to be well weigh'd on both ſides, eſpecially if they are of Conſequence and unalterable; in which Caſes our Duty and Wiſdom is to incline to that ſide, that hath the
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:106946:68"/> beſt Evidence, and the leaſt Hazards.</p>
            <p>Now for the Being of a God there are many weighty and preſſing Arguments, and as much Evidence as can be if he were; againſt it, there is no proof pretended, nor is it indeed capable of any; And which way now ought a prudent Man to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine his aſſent?</p>
            <p>If there be great Conveniences and no Danger on the one ſide, and if there be no Conveniences but vaſt Hazards on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, 'tis eaſie to ſee on what ſide all wiſe Men ought to incline: If there be no ſuch Being as a God, 'tis much for the Conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience of Mankind to believe and act as if there were, for hereby the publick Peace and Order of the World, together with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Man's private Benefit and Comfort are beſt preſerv'd; and there can be no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences in ſuch a Belief, but the caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing off a few ſenſual Luſts, which ſerve on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to make the preſent life troubleſom and uneaſie; and after this life, ſuppoſing there be no other, the good Man will fare as well as any: But if there be a God and a future ſtate after this, the Conveniences of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion will infinitely preponderate, for they that believe and ſerve him will be eternal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly happy; and they that disbelieve or neglect him ſhall be eternally and irreco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably miſerable.</p>
            <p>To conclude all, The Notion of a God being ſo evident, ſo weighty and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:106946:69"/> a Truth; being a Principle of Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ght, and the reſult of the Common reaſon of Mankind; let us make him the dayly Object of our Prayers and Praiſes, that as we receive Life and Breath and all things from him, ſo we may aſcribe all to him, and thankfully return him the Glory of all his Mercies; let us Love, Honour and Obey him in and above all things, whoſe infinite and adorable Perfections juſtly challenge theſe things from us.</p>
            <p>Let us live always in his Fear, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of offending him either in Thought, Word, or Deed.</p>
            <p>Let us make him the ſole Object of our Truſt and Affiance, repoſing all our Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in him, and committing our ſelves to him in well-doing.</p>
            <p>In a Word, Let us in all reſpects de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mean our ſelves towards him, as becometh Creatures to their Creator, paying him the conſtant Tribute of Religious Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip that is due to him, and ſerving him truly all the days of our Life; ſo ſhall we begin our Happineſs here by theſe imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Praiſes, which will be compleated here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after in the Eternal Fruition and Adoration of him: Which is the hearty Wiſh and Prayer of;</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>
                  <hi>SIR,</hi> 
               </salute>
               <signed>Your Faithful Friend and Servant, A. B.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:106946:69"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
